<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[DEFINITIVELY NOT JAMES]]></title><description><![CDATA[WORD WORDS WORDS WORDS]]></description><link>https://notjam.es</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 20:01:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[!{]giphy For some reason, Pokemon cards - first edition - are going for insane prices.
Folks are spending millions of dollars on them.  Part…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-28</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-28</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;!{]&lt;a href=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/GdOEOCxHIFwli/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;giphy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Pokemon cards - first edition - are going for insane prices.
Folks are spending &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/newsbeat-54507760&quot;&gt;millions of dollars&lt;/a&gt; on them.  Part of this
is because the sale of first edition cards like a Charizard have sold
for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Cardhops/status/1314756458668412928&quot;&gt;over $200,000 USD&lt;/a&gt;.  People are investing in Pokemon cards
instead of property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, because of this, we’re seeing an increase in fraudulent cards.
The most public of which is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/games/2020/oct/28/how-live-streamed-375k-deal-for-pokemon-cards-ended-in-disaster&quot;&gt;$375,000 USD box that ended up counterfeit&lt;/a&gt;.
This isn’t a new trend - art forgery has been documented even two thousand
years ago - where Roman sculptors produced copies of Greek sculptures.
However, at the time, it was very likely known by the art buyers
of the time that these were not genuine pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1496, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20210115080336/http://hoaxes.org/archive/permalink/michelangelos_cupid/&quot;&gt;Michelangelo sculpted a work of art - a sleeping cupid&lt;/a&gt;.
Through acid washing techniques, the piece was artificially aged
and sold to a cardinal - who learned that it was not a true antique.
However, being so impressed by Michelangelo’s talent, he let the young
artist keep the money he was paid.  It was still placed with other
true antiques, and was thus passed off as if it were one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It leads me to think about Phillip K Dick’s “The Man in the High Castle”.
In it, we have Frank Frink who makes and ages Colt Pistols as well as
other memorabilia.  Does it matter more that they are actual Colt Pistols
from the civil war?  Or that people that are collecting them can say that
they are?  It’s all in the “historicity”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Man in the High Castle, we have two Zippo lighters - one which is worth
a few dollars, and one which is worth $50,000.  Because of the historicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said, ‘what is “historicity”?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When a thing has history in it. Listen. One of those two Zippo lighters
was in Franklin D. Roosevelt’s pocket when he was assassinated. And one
wasn’t. One has historicity, a hell of a lot of it. As much as any object
ever had. And one has nothing … You can’t tell which is which.
There’s no “mystical plasmic presence”, no “aura” around it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much does it matter if the Shiny Charizard in Mint 9 condition
is a forgery if nobody could tell?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[A few studies published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
purport that we have biases towards class from even a few…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-27</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-27</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/WvuMTf88aV3FQ4odG5/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few studies published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
purport that &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.yale.edu/2019/10/21/yale-study-shows-class-bias-hiring-based-few-seconds-speech&quot;&gt;we have biases towards class from even a few seconds of speech&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is concerning but not unheard of.  There’s subjective standards in the English
language which people bias as being a perceived higher social class.  It changes
how we consider others.  Another followup study examines how this may affect
hiring managers’ assessment of qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the research is even more interesting because it shows that pronounciation
cues in speech gives a more accurate assessment as to someone’s social status
than the content.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Google Cloud is terrifying to some people because of Google’s policy of axeing products
all around. Steve Yegge penned an interesting blog…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-26</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-26</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/HgycnYQCMeJXO/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Cloud is terrifying to some people because of Google’s policy of axeing products
all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Yegge penned an &lt;a href=&quot;https://steve-yegge.medium.com/dear-google-cloud-your-deprecation-policy-is-killing-you-ee7525dc05dc&quot;&gt;interesting blog post&lt;/a&gt; about their experiences with Google
deprecation both from inside google and outside google.  In their case, they ran into
some of the same deprecation issues outside as they saw culturally on the inside.
Comparing it to AWS, there is a pretty stark difference in the deprecation policy
of old technology that isn’t actively being developed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deprecation isn’t the only oddity.  Quota increases can be weird, too - AWS asked me
to get my quota upped why and I wrote something, I don’t think they read it, and then
they upped it.  With Google, it was faster than AWS but I did have to talk to someone
on the phone in sales.  It felt weird.  Perhaps it’s a way to increase touch points
and push people to use more at GCP?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theinformation.com/articles/google-brass-set-2023-as-deadline-to-beat-amazon-microsoft-in-cloud&quot;&gt;Google has gone on record saying that they’ll end the GCP projects&lt;/a&gt; if they don’t
outclass Azure or AWS or the like.  That’s a tall order, and would require a much heavier
marketing and engineering push than I’ve been seeing.  They set the deadline to 2023,
so I’m sure we’ll see Google Cloud shutting down before 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knows, though, I’ve heard rumors of folks dog-fooding Google Cloud internally.
If Google Cloud could sign a deal as big as Google onto their cloud, I’m sure they’d
quickly outrank AWS, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s a Unicode proposal for Textile Care instructions.  This adds 40
new characters which represent instructions on how to wash your…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-22</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-22</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/6C5GbY5kB1pGeNXpRN/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Crissov/unicode-proposals/issues/410&quot;&gt;Unicode proposal for Textile Care instructions&lt;/a&gt;.  This adds 40
new characters which represent instructions on how to wash your clothes.
These are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iso.org/standard/42918.html&quot;&gt;ISO3758&lt;/a&gt;, which is the same as other international
standards that can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is based on work by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ginetex.net/&quot;&gt;GINETEX&lt;/a&gt;, an association for textile care
labels in Europe, South America, Africa, and Asia.  They’ve been working
on care labels since the late 60s &amp;#x26; pushing for regulation since the 70s.
If a nation is part of GINETEX, they mandate that the washing care instructions
follow correct use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, many of the GINETEX symbols are trademarked, thus can’t be used
freely in many European countries as part of the ISO3758 standard.  This is
partly because GINETEX wants to mandate the correct use of these symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, seriously, how do I wash my coat?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[University of Minnesota published a paper about vulnerabilities being
introduced to open source by malicious actors contributing commits…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-21</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-21</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/d2ZcfODrNWlA5Gg0/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/QiushiWu/QiushiWu.github.io/blob/main/papers/OpenSourceInsecurity.pdf&quot;&gt;University of Minnesota published a paper about vulnerabilities&lt;/a&gt; being
introduced to open source by malicious actors contributing commits.  They did
this by intentionally introducing bad code via merge requests to the Linux
kernel, leading to vulnerabilities.  Some of the 190 commits have
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/torvalds/linux/commit/8e949363f017&quot;&gt;even landed in stable branches&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethically, this is an
unacceptable behavior for experimentation, and has been reported to the UMN
Institutional Review Board on these cases.  Ethics complaints have also been
filed to IEEE to have the publication revoked, but it’s unlikely that it will
be.  They’ve also been &lt;a href=&quot;https://lore.kernel.org/linux-nfs/YH%2FfM%2FTsbmcZzwnX@kroah.com/&quot;&gt;banned, as a University, from contributing&lt;/a&gt; to the
Linux kernel, as well as from communicating through many Linux kernel mailing
lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their experiments prove that humans are fallible.  Good job, folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;*plonk*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Someone called out allowing disposable email as a security concern today. I disagree.  Disposable email is just another term for… email…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-16</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-16</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/3oz8xSwIOv5FGhZFjq/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone called out allowing disposable email as a security concern today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree.  Disposable email is just another term for… email.  Any email
service that you can sign up to.  Just that some are easier to sign up to than
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lighter-weight sign up email services are important for people that are
privacy conscious and want to control how they are interacted with more readily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about gmail?  Okay, I sign up once with example@gmail.com - then the next day
I sign up with e.xample@gmail.com - then e.x.a.mple@gmail.com - then example+1@gmail.com …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Disposable” email services are not the issue, here.  I don’t care if you use
a service that is “disposable” or “real” or not.  I can use any address @my-domain
and it will all work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that mean I run a disposable email service and I should be blocked?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[John Wilander, principal engineer on Intelligent Tracking Prevention in Safari,
opened an issue on the WICG FLoC github pointing out how…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-15</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-15</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l1Etd95mJdO2OkcHC/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Wilander, principal engineer on Intelligent Tracking Prevention in Safari,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/WICG/floc/issues/100&quot;&gt;opened an issue on the WICG FLoC github&lt;/a&gt; pointing out how FLoC can be used
to create cross-site tracking.  What this would mean is that the purported
privacy benefits of FLoC would be moot.  In fact, it would make it easier
to track a user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take this to the crowd metaphor: Before the pandemic and some time back,
I attended a Mew concert, a Ghost concert, Disney on Ice, and a Def Leppard
concert. At each of those events I was part of a large crowd. But I bet you
I was the only one to attend all four.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, de-anonymizing users is a huge problem.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2019/07/23/anonymous-data-might-not-be-so-anonymous-study-shows.html&quot;&gt;99% of Americans can be identified by 15 demographic attributes&lt;/a&gt;.
As part of this research, they &lt;a href=&quot;https://cpg.doc.ic.ac.uk/individual-risk/&quot;&gt;created a tool&lt;/a&gt; using just three
data points - ZIP code, gender, and birth date - which has an 83% chance
of identification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aren’t as anonymous as we’d like to think because we’re all wonderful and special
little snowflakes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[On November 18th, 2008, Heide Stefanyshyn-Piper looked out into the blue of
the ocean from 250 miles away.  Above it.  She kicked off for…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-14</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-14</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/xT5LMBATJuDO48jD44/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 18th, 2008, Heide Stefanyshyn-Piper looked out into the blue of
the ocean from 250 miles away.  Above it.  She kicked off for her third EVA for
mission &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/STS-126&quot;&gt;STS-126&lt;/a&gt;.  She was out there with fellow astronaut Stephen Bowen
to fix the rotation assembly that allows the solar arrays to follow the sun.
It had failed and was not operating optimally.  The solution that the
those ground control folks came up with?  Go out there with some grease
and some wipes to clean it up and grease it up.  No sweat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking into her airlock bag with these advanced tools she sees something
very concerning.  “I think we had a grease gun explode in the large bag.
There’s grease in the bag.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She heard Steve Bown observe dryly over her headset, “Ah. it must have been
the pressure changes.”  Putting that MIT engineering degree to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight controllers peered through her helmet camera uplink and calmly
assessed the situation, with suggestions.  She grabbed a dry wipe and did her
best to clean up the grease.  The EVA suit’s not known for being dextrous,
though, and one movement too exxagerated knocked the bag.  It tumbled away,
off on its own.  Out of reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, great. We have a lost tool, uh, I guess one of my crew lock bags was not
transferred and it’s loose.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&quot;https://spaceflightnow.com/shuttle/sts126/081118fd5/index2.html&quot;&gt;how one more piece of space debris&lt;/a&gt; ended up in orbit.  There are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://orbitaldebris.jsc.nasa.gov/faq/#faq03&quot;&gt;more than 23,000 pieces of debris larger than 10cm in orbit&lt;/a&gt;.  This number
grows every day.  Even something as small as Heide’s tool bag can be identified
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NJF8m0KbDZQ&quot;&gt;seen from the ground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space debris becomes more and more of a concern as we look outwards from our
own planet.  This is a problem known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kessler_syndrome&quot;&gt;Kessler syndrom&lt;/a&gt;.  The thought is
that a time could come where there’s such a density of space debris that
we avoiding collision would be impossible.  Even in the early 2000s we found
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20001121234600/http://www.space.com/scienceastronomy/planetearth/space_junk_000901.html&quot;&gt;evidence of small debris embedding itself in shuttle windows&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An impact with a piece of space debris is on average a collision with the
relative difference in velocity of 10-15km/s.  This is 10x the speed of even
the fastest bullets.  At that speed, even a bolt no bigger than your thumb will
tear through steel like paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s many &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuffin.space/&quot;&gt;projects to track and visualize space debris&lt;/a&gt;, but what do we
do to make this better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One approach is to stop putting things in higher orbits.  Low earth orbit has
a small amount of atmosphere which causes drag on items.  This means that,
without assistance, items in low earth orbit will leave orbit and return
to earth.  This is great because it puts a much shorter time limit on debris:
years instead of millenia.  This is why Starlink is considered less of a
negative impact on space debris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that still leaves thousands of tons of space junk in higher orbit.
Some of these will take many, many lifetimes before they would deorbit on their
own - perhaps longer.  Actively removing these takes ingenuity.  Science
fiction has looked into this active removal via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/video/vi1534902553&quot;&gt;movies&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planetes&quot;&gt;comics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, it’s more likely that we’ll use ground-based or sattelite-based
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_broom&quot;&gt;Laser Brooms&lt;/a&gt; to control and deorbit smaller debris (1cm-10cm in size).
This works by targeting a piece of debris and firing a high-power laser to heat
one side of the debris to produce thrust.  This would make the orbit unstable,
quickening the eventual deorbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and Heide’s toolbag.  It was in a low orbit on its own around Earth until
it lost enough velocity to return on August 3, 2009.  It was vaporized
during reentry.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Another Google product is being put out to pasture.  In particular,
“Google Play Movies & TV”.  Previously available content will be on…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-13</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-13</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/aOPINgmqpVXNK/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another Google product is being put out to pasture.  In particular,
“Google Play Movies &amp;#x26; TV”.  Previously available content will be on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/googleplay/thread/102498448?hl=en&quot;&gt;Youtube on Smart TVs&lt;/a&gt;.  The Android app has already been
rebranded to Google TV (not to be confused with &lt;a href=&quot;https://tv.google/&quot;&gt;Google TV&lt;/a&gt;).
This continues Google’s tradition of &lt;a href=&quot;https://killedbygoogle.com/&quot;&gt;killing products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Play Music was taken out a few months back, with Youtube
Music being the replacement.  This was such a difficult transition
that I started paying for Spotify for my parents to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand why this is (I am not a Xoogler and I am sure SOMEONE
here would have a clearer picture to this) it helps to understand
promotions at Google!  Promotions at higher levels have criteria
around impact to the organization and business.  A project that
creates a big splash will get people promoted.  This attracts people
to those projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, maintenance does not lead well to impact.  This
means that projects that aren’t shiny and new will bleed members
from their teams.  Maintenance work is a dead end because in most
cases, if you do your job right then nobody knows you’ve done
anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s totally understandable when you reframe it like this.
But nobody has to like it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Yet another great step for cryptocurrency enthusiasts, there’s now an
implementation of  backed by crytpo NFTs!  Exciting.
What does that…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-12</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-12</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/CDTUqFaYWBssS929Ou/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another great step for cryptocurrency enthusiasts, there’s now an
implementation of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;std::unique_ptr&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zhuowei/nft_ptr&quot;&gt;backed by crytpo NFTs&lt;/a&gt;!  Exciting.
What does that mean in practice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;std::unique_ptr&lt;/code&gt; in C++ is a smart &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pointer_(computer_programming)&quot;&gt;pointer&lt;/a&gt; that manages another
object via a pointer (a reference to a memory address).  What it does that
makes it “smart” is that it disposes of the object when the pointer goes out of
scope.  This is most often done using the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;delete&lt;/code&gt; operator, but can also be
supplied by the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This NFT pointer implementation has the same semantics and usability of a
traditional smart pointer, but also is on the Ethereum blockchain, making it
superior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we all know, adding blockchain to a problem automatically
makes it simple, transparent, and cryptographically secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference in performance between the two is negligible
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Age_of_the_universe&quot;&gt;in the grand scheme of things&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;std::unique_ptr&lt;/code&gt; running in
0.005 seconds, followed quickly behind by &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;nft_ptr&lt;/code&gt; at 3 minutes per call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applaud Zhuowei Zhang’s efforts to bring crytocurrency to more widespread
appeal.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/zhuowei/nft_ptr/main/white_paper.pdf&quot;&gt;For more information, check out their whitepaper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Amazon employees in Bessemer, Alabama voted against unionizing their
workplace.  There’s a lot that could be said about this - whether there…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-09</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-09</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0IyfjTLCd31N7xHq/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon employees in Bessemer, Alabama &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/amazon-is-ahead-in-union-vote-as-tallying-set-to-resume-11617960604&quot;&gt;voted against unionizing&lt;/a&gt; their
workplace.  There’s a lot that could be said about this - whether there was
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GrimKim/status/1380541382490738690&quot;&gt;some form of interference&lt;/a&gt; in the vote, or if it’s good or bad for the
employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bessemer,_Alabama#Economy&quot;&gt;Bessemer compared to other cities&lt;/a&gt;, it’s not
positive.  Manufacturing jobs dried up, unemployment rose, and crime increased.
It was voted &lt;a href=&quot;https://247wallst.com/special-report/2019/07/22/worst-cities-to-live-in-every-state-4/2/&quot;&gt;Alabama’s Worst City to Live in by 24/7 Wall Street.&lt;/a&gt;
The Amazon jobs are huge - given that AMZN is employing some 30% of the city.
For that city, at least short term, Amazon can be a great power for good.
Long term, who knows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As interesting as arguing about unions may be - let’s instead look at another
aspect of Amazon and how they interact with their workforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/amazon-employs-people-to-tweet-positively-about-warehouse-conditions-2018-8&quot;&gt;Fulfillment Center (FC) Ambassador Program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FC Ambassador Program is a way for fulfillment center employees can spend
one day a week tweeting about how great their job is at the warehouse.
They are trained to follow scripts, and don’t get much out of doing this
aside from an amazon gift card and one limited paid day off
(with an expiration of 3 weeks).  This ends up with great tweets such as
the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know that Amazon pays warehouse workers 30% more than other
retailers? I feel proud to work for Amazon – they’ve taken good
care of me. Much better than some of my previous employers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Shaye – Amazon FC Ambassador 📦 (@AmazonFCShaye)
August 21, 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re often the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/readkrystalhu/status/1033112717589204994&quot;&gt;“kiss asses” of the departments&lt;/a&gt;.  Who can blame, them,
though?  Getting out of loading and unloading trucks for 10 hours and all
you have to do is write some tweets?  I’d be tempted, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continue to slowly tread towards the Amazon dystopia we never wanted.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[We’re moving away from fossil fuels in our day to day transit as electric
vehicles are becoming more viable for our transportation needs…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-08</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-08</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/iqryv05RJMVlm/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re moving away from fossil fuels in our day to day transit as electric
vehicles are becoming more viable for our transportation needs.  However,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/cycling-is-ten-times-more-important-than-electric-cars-for-reaching-net-zero-cities-157163&quot;&gt;pushing people to use bicycles more&lt;/a&gt; would be far more helpful than
pushing for a transition to electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electric Vehicles &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eea.europa.eu/publications/transport-and-environment-report-2020&quot;&gt;are far from carbon neutral&lt;/a&gt;.  They’re better than
combustion engine vehicles, of course, but the production and manufacturing of
the batteries and chassis still produces a large amount of emissions.
The generation of electricity to charge these electric vehicles is also
not carbon-zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushing for bicycles works in urban cities.  Especially those with milder
climates.  However, most articles gloss over rural areas with more extreme
climates.  It’s one thing to try to trudge around New York City when it’s a
humid 95F / 35C day.  It’s uncomfortable and you might end up a little sweaty.
It’s an entirely different story to bike the 35 miles from Frisco, Texas into
downtown Dallas during the 115F / 46C summer.  It’s downright dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bicycling is great if it’s an option - but it own’t be for everyone.  While
electric vehicles aren’t entirely carbon zero, they’re better than many
alternatives while being feasible “replacements”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you’re in a city and can bike somewhere?  Do that.  It’s healthier, too.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Dungeons and Dragons, is first and foremost, a collaborative storytelling game.
Sure, there might be lots of numbers and mechanics to…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-07</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-07</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0ExsgrTuACbtPaqQ/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dungeons and Dragons, is first and foremost, a collaborative storytelling game.
Sure, there might be lots of numbers and mechanics to support these stories.
Without those, there’s a whole lot of chaos.  At the end of the day, though,
all of the rules can be blurred or broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why the Dungeon Master is always looked upon as a supreme being of
grand benevolence.  It’s also why there’s one rule that has withstood the test
of time: The Rule… of Cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s one of the first things you often get told when you ask a seasoned
storyteller for DnD for advice.  The Rule of Cool is simple, really.  If it’s
cool?  Why not let it play out?  Of course, cool is subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the deal: You’re playing with friends.  You want your friends to all
feel like they are the most amazing people. (Spoiler: They are.)  So the
Rule of Cool can be used as a fantastic reward to those wonderful players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite rule of cool I’d been part of was when an Orc fighter, Human Druid,
an Elven Cleric, and a Gnome Barbarian were in dire straits.  They’d been a
Big Bad Evil Wizard for an hour - and had nearly taken them down.  Right
as they were going to strike the final blow, the wizard had opened a magical
portal (Dimension Door) towards their friend and compatriot, the Elven Cleric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’d knocked them unconcious with a magic weapon attack, and the cleric
was barely holding onto their mortal coil.  None of the three had enough time
to get over the difficult terrain to the Big Bad to save their friend.  A
friend that they’d gotten close with over months. Someone they cared about.
In less than 6 seconds they knew it would be the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except… what if… So the Orc player stared straight at our DM and declared
their next action.  “I’m going to do a fastball special.”  They were declaring
that they’d PICK UP the Gnome and throw them as hard as they could at the
Big Bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DM’s eyebrow raised as they opened up their rulebook, looked a bit, and
closed it.  We all knew there was nothing in there about this.  It’s just not
part of the rules.  We all knew what the answer would be.
“I don’t think you can throw them quite that far.  That’s 90 feet.”  We were
all a little slack jawed.  Our DM had always followed the rules to a T… up
until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our druid’s eyes light up.  “GUST OF WIND!  I HAVE A TURN.  GUST OF WIND.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a bit of contemplation, the DM sighed.  “Alright.”  Pointing at the Orc,
“You roll strength.”  Pointing at the Druid, “You roll wisdom”.
Pointing at the Gnome, “You roll for an attack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strength, 19, plus 4.  “You see her muscles ripple, and our Gnomish friend
feels like there is an incredibly springboard under his feet.  Before he has
even a moment to think through how awful this plan is, he’s rocketed into the
air.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wisdom, 16, plus 3.  “Druidic energy starts to emenate visibly from the staff,
and all of you can hear a howling of wind through the trees picking up.
While soaring through the air, the Gnome accelerates even faster - the wind
screaming by their ears.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attack roll, natural 20.  The gnome barbarian stares at the die, worried that
it might change if they don’t keep a close eye on it.  “The wizard’s eyes go
wide, as he starts to utter an incantation - but not fast enough.  You feel a
CRUNCH as you slam into his chest, axes flying from a mix of momentum and
your rage.  Your vision is blood red.  You can hear your own pulse pounding in
your ears.  Uhh.. you have brutal critical, don’t you.  He’s only got..”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DM looked up quietly from behind their cardboard DM screen, they stole
Matt Mercer’s line, with a giant grin growing across their face.
“How do you want to do this?”  We broke a lot of rules - but we all felt like
heroes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Disney World is a monumental effort to make it the Most Magical place on Earth.
Much of this is attributed to the extreme amounts of…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-06</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-06</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l4KhR3XppupHtGNk4/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney World is a monumental effort to make it the Most Magical place on Earth.
Much of this is attributed to the extreme amounts of engineering that have
gone into manufacturing the magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the Utilidor is the best example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you’re at Disney World, you’re technically on the rooftop of the
Magic Kingdom.  A portmanteau of Utility and Corridor, the Utilidor is the
true “first floor” of the theme park.  In most places in Florida, you dig a
few feet down?  You hit water.  Building underground is thus mostly a
dangerous and difficult proposition.  Thus, most of the Magic Kingdom is
about 100ft above sea level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Utilidor is used for logistics in the park.  Getting anything from point
A to point B magically can be done via the tunnel systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employees (referred to as “Cast Members” per corporate mandate) travel between
locations using the Utilidor.  This allows them to navigate quickly using
electric vehicles &amp;#x26; get in the correct locations quickly for their work.
The Utilidor also houses a number of services for employees - such as
cafeterias, banking services, hair salons, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I think is the most interesting, however, is the automated vacuum waste
collection within the Utilidor.  The utilidor has pneumatic tubes to quickly
whisk away any and all trash away from the park - to where it can be
disposed of or recycled.  This helps the custodial staff keep the park as
clean as it is - by taking all the trash and dumping it somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are “Backstage” tours of Walt Disney World that show off the utilidor
among other ways that the magic is preserved at the theme park.  Even if
some of the illusion can be dispelled, though, it’s still real magic if you
believe in it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Supreme Court has come to a decision on the Google v Oracle case
regarding Google’s usage of the Java SE API in Android’s Android…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-05</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-05</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0MYA6gVfB7CcdkR2/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/20pdf/18-956_d18f.pdf&quot;&gt;come to a decision&lt;/a&gt; on the Google v Oracle case
regarding Google’s usage of the Java SE API in Android’s Android Runtime,
as well as Dalvik VM before it. This has been ongoing since August 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TLDR: It’s fair use, the declaring code is very small and is not
implementation, but instead a general organization. As such, it’s fair use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s read a couple excerpts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most succinct description of how this is fair use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google copied these lines not because of their creativity or beauty but
because they would allow programmers to bring their skills to a new
smartphone computing environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But does this mean that programs in general are not copyrightable?
The following decides that’s not the case:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of an interface, the copied lines are inherently
bound together with uncopyrightable ideas (the overall organization of
the API) and the creation of new creative expression (the code inde-
pendently written by Google). Unlike many other computer programs,
the value of the copied lines is in significant part derived from the in-
vestment of users (here computer programmers) who have learned the
API’s system. Given these differences, application of fair use here is
unlikely to undermine the general copyright protection that Congress
provided for computer programs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much of the code is considered copied:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one considers the declaring code in isolation, the quan-
titative amount of what Google copied was large. Google
copied the declaring code for 37 packages of the Sun Java
API, totaling approximately 11,500 lines of code. Those
lines of code amount to virtually all the declaring code
needed to call up hundreds of different tasks. On the other
hand, if one considers the entire set of software material in
the Sun Java API, the quantitative amount copied was
small. The total set of Sun Java API computer code, includ-
ing implementing code, amounted to 2.86 million lines, of
which the copied 11,500 lines were only 0.4 percent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my favorite part of the entire decision is that they retell one of
the world’s shortest short stories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he awoke, the dinosaur was still there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s a really neat stack overflow post about the
Amiga OS Kickstart image.  They ask why the image included during the
bootstrapping…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-02</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-02</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/hsxg9x2LrmTNC/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a really neat &lt;a href=&quot;https://retrocomputing.stackexchange.com/questions/13897/why-was-the-kickstart-1-x-insert-floppy-graphic-so-bad/13901&quot;&gt;stack overflow post&lt;/a&gt; about the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AmigaOS&quot;&gt;Amiga OS&lt;/a&gt; Kickstart image.  They ask why the image included during the
bootstrapping sequence of the Amiga computers - known as “Kickstart” - was so
ugly.  The image showed up and instructed the user to insert the Kickstart
floppy so the computer could start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short version is that they were severely resource constrained.  A bitmap
payload would have been around 4KiB, but vector art data for the Kickstart
image weighed in at only 412 bytes.  This was very important when they only
had 8KiB of space to work with for the pre-boot ROM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vector art data is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;hex&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-hex line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-hex&quot;&gt;FF 01 23 0B 3A 0B 3A 21 71 21 71 0B 7D 0B 88 16 88 5E 7F 5E 7F 38 40 38
3E 36 35 36 34 38 2D 38 2D 41 23 48 23 0B FE 02 25 45 FF 01 21 48 21 0A
7E 0A 8A 16 8A 5F 56 5F 56 64 52 6C 4E 71 4A 74 44 7D 3C 81 3C 8C 0A 8C
0A 6D 09 6D 09 51 0D 4B 14 45 15 41 19 3A 1E 37 21 36 21 36 1E 38 1A 3A
16 41 15 45 0E 4B 0A 51 0A 6C 0B 6D 0B 8B 28 8B 28 76 30 76 34 72 34 5F
32 5C 32 52 41 45 41 39 3E 37 3B 37 3E 3A 3E 41 3D 42 36 42 33 3F 2A 46
1E 4C 12 55 12 54 1E 4B 1A 4A 17 47 1A 49 1E 4A 21 48 FF 01 32 3D 34 36
3C 37 3D 3A 3D 41 36 41 32 3D FF 01 33 5C 33 52 42 45 42 39 7D 39 7D 5E
34 5E 33 5A FF 01 3C 0B 6F 0B 6F 20 3C 20 3C 0B FF 01 60 0E 6B 0E 6B 1C
60 1C 60 0E FE 03 3E 1F FF 01 62 0F 69 0F 69 1B 62 1B 62 0F FE 02 63 1A
FF 01 2F 39 32 39 32 3B 2F 3F 2F 39 FF 01 29 8B 29 77 30 77 35 72 35 69
39 6B 41 6B 41 6D 45 72 49 72 49 74 43 7D 3B 80 3B 8B 29 8B FF 01 35 5F
35 64 3A 61 35 5F FF 01 39 62 35 64 35 5F 4A 5F 40 69 3F 69 41 67 3C 62
39 62 FF 01 4E 5F 55 5F 55 64 51 6C 4E 70 49 71 46 71 43 6D 43 6A 4E 5F
FF 01 44 6A 44 6D 46 70 48 70 4C 6F 4D 6C 49 69 44 6A FF 01 36 68 3E 6A
40 67 3C 63 39 63 36 65 36 68 FF 01 7E 0B 89 16 89 5E FE 01 22 0B FE 01
3B 0B FE 01 61 0F FE 01 6A 1B FE 01 70 0F FE 01 7E 5E FE 01 4B 60 FE 01
2E 39 FF FF&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it was interpreted followed pretty simple rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read two bytes at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If both bytes are &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;FF&lt;/code&gt;, end the program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the first byte is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;FF&lt;/code&gt; and the second byte is not, start drawing a polyline with the color index given in the second byte. Treat any subsequent two bytes as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;x,y&lt;/code&gt; coordinates belonging to that polyline except if the first byte is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;FF&lt;/code&gt; (see rules 2 and 3) or &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;FE&lt;/code&gt; (see rule 4), which is where you stop drawing the line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the first byte is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;FE&lt;/code&gt;, flood fill an area using the color index given in the second byte, starting from the point whose coordinates are given in the next two bytes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://eab.abime.net/showpost.php?p=1159886&amp;#x26;postcount=52&quot;&gt;Sheryl Knowles&lt;/a&gt;, the first Amiga artist, noted that there were no real
tools on the Amiga to make many of these images aside from when they
eventually wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amiga_software&quot;&gt;Graphicraft&lt;/a&gt;.  At that point, using graphicraft she
held the floppy in her left hand and painstakingly created the drawing with
her right hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The drawing was limited in size and in the number of pixels that could be
used, by the programming requirements of the time. All of which should
explain why it’s a bad drawing. But it was deemed a sufficient icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is very true!  Even if it’s ugly, it’s clear what it’s supposed to be.
It’s not supposed to be high art - it’s supposed to be an icon you see for a
couple seconds at most.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today, running 5KM took a lot out of me.  This can be squarely blamed
on a more sedentary lifestyle than is ideal.  This doesn’t mean I can…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-04-01</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-04-01</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/6Z3D5t31ZdoNW/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, running 5KM took a lot out of me.  This can be squarely blamed
on a more sedentary lifestyle than is ideal.  This doesn’t mean I can’t.
We’re all &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/IxuThNgl3YA&quot;&gt;Born to Run&lt;/a&gt; in our own ways.  Some hypotheses even suggest that
we should take that pretty literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rar%C3%A1muri&quot;&gt;Rarámuri&lt;/a&gt; peoples - 5KM might feel like a lot,
but they’re known to long-distance running.  Extremely long-distance running.
Up to 320KM in one session, often over the course of multiple days.  That isn’t
even on flat surfaces, either.  It’s through canyon and brush, with rather
significant elevation changes and rough terrain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s more, the Rarámuri also have competitive aspects to their running,
such as the game &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rarajipari&quot;&gt;Rarajipari&lt;/a&gt; - a game of kicking and chasing a ball.  Even
casual games will go on for several miles.  However, after some serious
all-night partying they will do equally serious matches which go on for thirty
to fourty miles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While much of that can seem extreme, it’s led many to lean into the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endurance_running_hypothesis&quot;&gt;Endurance running hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; - that certain human characteristics can be
explained by our need to run extended distances.  Sure, it’s just a hypothesis,
and there’s definitely some areas where it falters - but it’s interesting
nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example - we have shorter toes than other primates.  For grasping, this
makes us greatly inferior.  We lost overall strength and gripping capabilities.
With such short toes, how am I supposed to hang from the monkey bars with just
my toes?  However, shorter toes mean less mechanical work is needed to support
weight.  Less exertion is put on the joints, and we can support 75% of our body
weight on just our toes.  In running, this is incredibly important - as we often
will end up landing on our toes - and those longer toes would cause injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it all mean, though?  Well, you might not run 300KM in a single go
today - but I’m sure 5KM is a good start on it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[;l;;gmlxzssaw]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-30</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-30</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/Sw5EsuT5VI3aU/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikaelThalen/status/1376653334396903428&quot;&gt;;l;;gmlxzssaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Suez canal is clear again. Hackernews was suggesting a wide array of possible solutions. You can vibrate the sand with the right…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-29</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-29</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/LqW9dLVjQm3cs/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Suez canal is clear again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hackernews was suggesting a wide array of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can vibrate the sand with the right resonance to “liquefy” the sand
allowing for easier passage - similar &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tV4sTbpa7Hc&quot;&gt;to concrete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use heavy-lift helicopters to unload the shipping containers
to.. somewhere.  An empty shipping container is 4 tons.  A fully-loaded
container is 33.5 tons.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mil_Mi-26&quot;&gt;Mi-26&lt;/a&gt; is the largest and most powerful
helicopter to go into serial production and it can only lift 14.5 tons.
This would be roughly 60-240 minutes per container to offload, assuming
the helicopters don’t have failures.  At a 20k ton load that puts us at
175 days, give or take to unload the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could cut through the ship - &lt;a href=&quot;https://jalopnik.com/a-chain-just-cut-through-a-capsized-cargo-ship-filled-w-1845784581&quot;&gt;it’s been done before&lt;/a&gt;.  It’d be a huge
loss for ths shipping company, though.  It’d also take many months, and
would likely destroy all of the cargo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could do what they do with beached whales - just blow it up.  Evaporate
it with an ICBM.  Let’s ignore various nuclear arms treaties and ecological
issues involved.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGM-118_Peacekeeper&quot;&gt;LGM-118 Peacekeeper&lt;/a&gt; is armed with a 300 kiloton
W87 warhead.  Unfortunately, the Ever Given is just too big.  It would not
be completely destroyed as the fireball is only 320 meters and various
leftover scrap metal would be all over the place.  Upgrading to something
that would make the UN sweat a little, though, and we could probably
create a big enough crater to allow for U-turns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite, though… is to just explode a medium sized nuke under the ship.
Then another.  Then another.  Just keep exploding nukes until it’s sailing
off into the cosmos.  We’d have accomplished &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Orion_(nuclear_propulsion)&quot;&gt;Project Orion&lt;/a&gt;.
Open up the Suez canal and ship goods to Mars in one fell swoop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, the Suez canal was cleared by high tide, dredging the canal,
and a bunch of tug boats.  Keep it Simple.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[While Ireland’s Gaeilge is the national and official language of the Republic of Ireland,
many regions of Ireland speak a dialect of English…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-19</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-19</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/2z0OViv5TdAGs/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uni-due.de/DI/&quot;&gt;Ireland’s Gaeilge&lt;/a&gt; is the national and official language of the Republic of Ireland,
many regions of Ireland speak a dialect of English: Hiberno-English, or Irish English.
Even within this dialect there’s a number of differences regionally, which have developed
over hundreds of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;English has been pushing out Gaeilge in Ireland for centuries.  Originally brought
to Ireland in the 12th century via the Norman Invasion, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudor_conquest_of_Ireland&quot;&gt;Tudor conquest&lt;/a&gt;
led to English speaking immigrants flooding Ireland, and a general suppresion of
the Irish language.  More recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cso.ie/en/releasesandpublications/ep/p-cp10esil/p10esil/ilg/&quot;&gt;only 4% of surveyed Irish speakers&lt;/a&gt;
speak Gaelige in their daily life.  Otherwise, English is the predominant language
of the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the English attempted suppress anything other than the traditional
English at the time, there’s been a number of differences that have grown to
make Irish English unique across the gamut - grammar, vocabulary, and phonetics,
Much of this is holdover from Gaelige, which makes it doubly interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One particularly interesting grammatical difference is that “yes” and “no” are
far less frequently used.  For example, “You speak with an Irish dialect?” would
be responded with “I do” instead of “Yes”.  Much of this is due to
the Irish language lacking “yes” or “no” as vocabulary.  Instead,
the verb is negated and responded with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiberno-English pulls a number of words from Gaeilge as loan-words, as well
as some that are merely derived from the national language.  “Sláinte!” is
one that you might hear in a pub, meaning “(To your) Health!”  And if you’re
nervous, you might “fooster” - to fidget - derived from the Gaeilge word
“Fústar”.  In other cases, Hiberno-English has vocabulary that is less
clearly historied - such as when you’ve really broken something?  It’s
“banjaxed”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phonology of Hiberno-English is probably what differs the most between
the regions.  I’ll be frank - I’m not a phonetics expert, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/84678944.pdf&quot;&gt;every paper&lt;/a&gt;
I’ve read on this really goes all out on that.  A few examples, however,
are words like “kite” that to American ears would sound like “koyt”,
“mouth” which would be closer to “meh-ooth” or “maith”, and
“about” would be close to “a boat”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now don’t be a lúdramán, and give céad míle fáilte when yer with the Irish, will you?
They do be thinking yer an eejit if ya talk like this, yeah?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Thank you for subscribing to Cat Facts. Cats recognize our voices but don’t care. Cats get separation anxiety but handle that by peeing on…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-18</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-18</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/xJjs8eGVbjNYY/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for subscribing to Cat Facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/cats-recognise-their-owners-voices-never-evolved-care-says-study-8966580.html&quot;&gt;Cats recognize our voices but don’t care&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://avmajournals.avma.org/doi/abs/10.2460/javma.2002.220.1028?journalCode=javma&quot;&gt;Cats get separation anxiety but handle that by peeing on all of your stuff&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://animalbehaviorandcognition.org/uploads/journals/30/AB_C_2021_Vol8(1)_Chijiiwa_et_al.pdf&quot;&gt;Cats don’t mind if someone’s mean to you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that they’re awful in any way - it’s just their nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#x3C;To cancel Daily Cat Facts, reply ‘STOP’&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last year Gregg Tavares posted about Github’s permission model,
frustrated with how it blindly grants the ability to request data from users…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-17</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-17</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l41lOUyXuBnZrckYU/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year &lt;a href=&quot;https://games.greggman.com/game/github-permission-problem/&quot;&gt;Gregg Tavares posted about Github’s permission model&lt;/a&gt;,
frustrated with how it blindly grants the ability to request data from users
to anyone that asks for the permissions.  Yesterday it was trending on
Hackernews.  I think from a privacy standpoint it’s an interesting read.
Something they touched on, however, gave me that weird gut feeling…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s imagine your bank let you sign in to 3rd party services in a similar
manner. How many people would click through on “Let ACME corp act on your
behalf on your Citibank Account”. I think most people would be super scared
of permissions like that. Instead they’d want very specific permission
like, only permission to deposit money, or only permission to read the
balance, or only permission to read transactions, etc…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, you sweet summer child.  Oh, no, no, no.  It’s much worse when it comes
to banking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Plaid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might know Plaid because their Visa acquisiton was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov/opa/pr/visa-and-plaid-abandon-merger-after-antitrust-division-s-suit-block&quot;&gt;recently blocked&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plaid operates as an “in-between” for their customers to allow end-users
to sign into banks - surfacing information about account numbers,
routing numbers, current balance, recent transactions, and other related
banking information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, let’s pull apart how that works.  Let’s take Venmo as an example.
Venmo embeds Plaid’s SDK.  A user will want to link their bank account to
Venmo.  The SDK interacts with and then Plaid performs a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack&quot;&gt;Man in the Middle&lt;/a&gt; attack on the end-user.  Within an app (not the bank’s)
app, Plaid’s embeddable code will simulate a fake bank login, collect
credentials - including many 2FA - and then falsify a login as if they were
an end user.  At this point they scrape all data they can get access to,
storing it all in their servers.  This is how their customers, like Venmo,
would be able to verify you own your account and can peek at your account
balance to verify you have funds to pay for that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mentalfloss.com/article/86907/here-are-most-popular-transactions-made-through-venmo&quot;&gt;pizza / rent / drugs / fantasy football&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plaid’s codebase itself has a distinct issue, too.  The underlying code for
their scrapers are thousands upon thousands of Python files that connect
together like spaghetti.  Updates get patched in at random, so following
security practices is attempted but… it’s a moving target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as permissioning - it’s nonexistent.  Plaid gives every single one of
their customers full access to the accounts of users that authenticated.
With Venmo - account verification?  Sure!  Account balance?  Uh.. weird, but
okay.  Loan status?  Credit card statements?  Transactions unrelated to Venmo?
Identity documentation?  Initiate transfers? &lt;a href=&quot;https://plaid.com/docs/api/accounts/#accountsget&quot;&gt;Uhh.. Why?!  For anyone?!!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this legal?  Well, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americanbanker.com/news/lawsuit-against-plaid-heightens-focus-on-data-privacy-issues&quot;&gt;maybe&lt;/a&gt;.  That doesn’t stop
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctvnews.ca/business/td-bank-files-lawsuit-against-plaid-accusing-it-of-trying-to-dupe-consumers-1.5145326&quot;&gt;banks from suing Plaid&lt;/a&gt;.  This is also not great for consumers because it
opens up new vectors for threat actors to gain access to accounts and could
void agreements banks have with their customers around fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of financial services apps like Mint also work in this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry, though, at least we can use alternatives.  Like, I’ve heard of
“Yodlee” to do this, right? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thetrustedinsight.com/investment-news/yodlee-jumpshot-data-problems-impact-on-hedge-funds-other-data-providers-20200304832/&quot;&gt;Oh…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, services like Plaid provide features that users want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do I think plaid is a security nightmare?  &lt;strong&gt;Yes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I think of a reasonable alternative for their features?  &lt;strong&gt;No.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Docker announced a Series B raise of $23M today - which is definitely impressive
for a company focused around Open-Source, right?  Well…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-16</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-16</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/cUMNWzWZ5n75LvcCIe/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/press-release/Docker-Series-B&quot;&gt;Docker announced a Series B raise of $23M&lt;/a&gt; today - which is definitely impressive
for a company focused around Open-Source, right?  Well, maybe.  In 2015, Docker
&lt;a href=&quot;https://venturebeat.com/2015/04/14/docker-raises-95m-led-by-insight-venture-partners/&quot;&gt;had announced a $95M Series D raise of funding at a $1B valuation&lt;/a&gt;.  Best
guess was a reset after Mirantis acquired part of the company?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s Docker the software?  Let’s start with the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Containers.  Containers are effectively packaging to create a running process
with encapsulation features applied to keep it isolated from when
running on a host computer.  Containers as a concept have been around for
decades - older examples would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenVZ&quot;&gt;OpenVZ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Containers are helpful for developing software because they provide portability,
reproducibility, and isolation.  Portability helps you run your app anywhere -
irregardless of the system you’re running on.  Isolation is so that state in
the host and state in other Containers won’t impact your app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is different from virtual machines that have full virtualization.
Containers will often utilize OS virtualization &amp;#x26; isolation features to
share multiple containers safely in one OS - instead of a full VM where the
OS is duplicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That leads to Docker the Software.  Docker the software brings container
tooling, an abstraction layer wrapping multiple Virtualization APIs, and a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-specific_language&quot;&gt;Domain Specific Language&lt;/a&gt; for Container Filesystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Docker’s “images” include everything needed to start a container - the code or
binary, runtimes, dependencies, and any other filesystem objects required.
Docker images and containers are supported by most of the big cloud providers -
AMZN AWS, GOOG Cloud, MSFT Azure, Heroku, Glitch, and others.  The same docker
image can be run across all of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does Docker Inc do?  Docker, Inc primarily develops Docker Hub and
Docker Desktop at this point in time.  Per their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/blog/helping-dev-teams-get-ship-done/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about their
plans for the funding it seems like they’re focusing on improving dev
experience, tooling around security, and API development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve got high hopes for the company into the 2020s.  Here’s hoping that this
time investor interests are more closely aligned with the direction of the
company.  If not, I’m sure we’ll see Docker repeat the past decade again.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Security.txt made the rounds again on HackerNews.  It’s a format,
similar to robots.txt for making it clearer how to submit security
issues…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-15</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-15</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/dFpG6KdpSEzC0/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://securitytxt.org/&quot;&gt;Security.txt&lt;/a&gt; made the rounds again on HackerNews.  It’s a format,
similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robots_exclusion_standard&quot;&gt;robots.txt&lt;/a&gt; for making it clearer how to submit security
issues to an organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, this is great!  It’s noted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cyber.dhs.gov/bod/20-01/&quot;&gt;the DHS&lt;/a&gt; as a helpful way for
researchers to communicate their findings.  At one point, it was required
for agencies to have it, but was removed from that draft.   Because it’s at a
normalized location, it can be found by scraping sites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shodan.io/search?query=http.securitytxt%3Acontact&quot;&gt;SHODAN&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.disclose.io/&quot;&gt;Disclose.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, however, &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19152145&quot;&gt;some members of the cyber security community&lt;/a&gt; find it
to leads to a poor signal-to-noise ratio.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some entrepeneurial members of the cybersecurity community will grab the
domain lists with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;security.txt&lt;/code&gt; files, fetch the email, run &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1639985&quot;&gt;burpsuite&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.rapid7.com/2011/12/08/six-ways-to-automate-metasploit/&quot;&gt;metasploit&lt;/a&gt; to get some low effort security issues, and dump it all into
excel.  For extra credit, then do a &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/use-mail-merge-for-bulk-email-letters-labels-and-envelopes-f488ed5b-b849-4c11-9cff-932c49474705&quot;&gt;mail-merge&lt;/a&gt;.  Minimal effort, and if
you get answers back you ask for a bug bounty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think that &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;security.txt&lt;/code&gt; on its own will cause this, though.  It’s
just as easy to search for Vulnerability Disclosure Policies and use those as
inputs for automated security testing.  It takes a bit more manual work, but
even with that you end up with odd security reports now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is to explain how we ended up with the security report for a site
that shared the same first two letters of ours instead.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The UK is in talks to depart from using GDPR.  This likely means
one of two outcomes - neither of which are positive. Option A - come up…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-12</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-12</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/7zoAI7BIrzT1e/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lawgazette.co.uk/news/uk-to-depart-from-gdpr/5107685.article&quot;&gt;UK is in talks to depart from using GDPR&lt;/a&gt;.  This likely means
one of two outcomes - neither of which are positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Option A - come up with their own privacy laws.  This is iffy and is the path
the USA is currently on.  You end up with multiple laws that may by chance hit
similar beats but may conflict and make it more difficult to be compliant.  In
this world, many companies will just ignore the privacy laws in the hopes that
they won’t be caught - or that the legal jurisdiction they’re in makes it
difficult to litigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Option B - roll back everything.  This is bad for privacy, consumers, and
citizens of the UK but good for businesses.  As such, this is the likely path
forward, given other recent actions taken by parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we continue to split up privacy laws, I’ve got a bad feeling about the
future of the internet.  I could foresee a future where it’s no longer open
across country borders and becomes insular within each jurisdiction, sharing
stamped out by bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Amen Brother by The Winstons is a B-side of The Winston’s 1969 single
“Color Him Father”.  The A-side song - “Color Him Father” - won a…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-11</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-11</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/uKWE6qMrVOEEg/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/GxZuq57_bYM&quot;&gt;Amen Brother by The Winstons&lt;/a&gt; is a B-side of The Winston’s 1969 single
“Color Him Father”.  The A-side song - “Color Him Father” - won a Grammy Award
for Best R&amp;#x26;B song in 1970 - but the B-side… the B-side has been heard by
so many more people.  Not in its entirety, mind you, but in the seven second
drum solo from 1 minute and 26 seconds to 1 minute and 33 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the “Amen Break”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drum solo, performed by Greg Coleman, was initially just meant to fill time.
It caught the attention of DJs almost two decades later in the hip-hop scene.
They found that if you slowed it down from 135BPM to about 90BPM it became the
perfect canvas for laid back rappers to create on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Coleman was unlikely to have become aware of the impact he had
on the world.  George Coleman died in 2006, homeless and destitute.  However,
his drum solo is immortal and has shaped modern music as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s thousands upon thousands of songs that use the Amen Break, but I’ll
leave you with a few I’m fond of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/7lEB7V-KIb0&quot;&gt;Mindfields&lt;/a&gt; by The Prodigy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/b-I2s5zRbHg&quot;&gt;You Know I’m No Good&lt;/a&gt; by Amy Winehouse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/wmin5WkOuPw&quot;&gt;Firestarter&lt;/a&gt; by The Prodigy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/TMZi25Pq3T8&quot;&gt;Straight Outta Compton&lt;/a&gt; by NWA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/2PBeKzVhWHY&quot;&gt;Szamar Madar&lt;/a&gt; by Venetian Snares&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/wusSmIV-FE8&quot;&gt;I Desire&lt;/a&gt; by Salt-N-Pepa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MWCSw_cNxKc&quot;&gt;Come On My Selector&lt;/a&gt; by Squarepusher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MqbQC81_74k&quot;&gt;Little Wonder&lt;/a&gt; by David Bowie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/QRk1s5Kf3aQ&quot;&gt;The Theme for Futurama&lt;/a&gt; by Christopher Tyng&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/5qajT8lS2ok&quot;&gt;Finale&lt;/a&gt; by Toby Fox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Oh no!  OVH had a small datacenter fire which affected their SBG datacenter.
This is not that uncommon of a problem for a datacenter.  That…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-10</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-10</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/8Ep2aFnTfs6TC/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh no!  OVH had a small &lt;a href=&quot;http://travaux.ovh.net/?do=details&amp;#x26;id=49471&amp;#x26;&quot;&gt;datacenter fire&lt;/a&gt; which affected their SBG datacenter.
This is not that uncommon of a problem for a datacenter.  That’s why you should
always have a Disaster Recovery Plan if your data is invaluable - beyond
reliance on fire suppression systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fire suppression in datacenters pose an interesting problem.  When you have
so many things that can’t get wet and are incredibly expensive to replace
you can’t use sprinklers, and any residue could be heavily damaging
to the equipment as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bromotrifluoromethane&quot;&gt;Bromotrifluoromethane&lt;/a&gt;, or Halon, was developed in the 1950s as a
gaseous fire suppression agent for use with valuable materials - such
as computers and telecommunications systems.  In the mid-90s we stopped
using Halon because it is incredibly damaging to the ozone layer and
contributes considerably towards global warming.  However much damage
it causes to the planet, it’s relatively safe for humans.  While Halon
may cause dizziness and tingling in the extremities at the low amounts
it may be effective at, it is relatively safe to be used in close
quarters.  This is why even now the FAA reccommends it for aircraft!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1,1,1,2,3,3,3-Heptafluoropropane&quot;&gt;HFC-227ea&lt;/a&gt; is another gaseous fire suppression agent used in data centers.
Generally, this is safe for humans at up to 9% concentration, which is the
maximum most fire suppression systems would use.  It doesn’t deplete the ozone
layer but does contribute to climate change in other ways.  At incredibly high
heat, however, it does decompose into hydrogen fluoride - which can cause
blindness and creates hydrofluoric acid on contact with moisture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most fire suppression systems have an alarm before they go off and may
be manually prevented.  If you’re interested, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/QUZ83WcedK0&quot;&gt;a simulation video&lt;/a&gt;
video which has some obnoxious music but is otherwise accurate.  I’ve been part
of this before in a data center, and it’s not a fun time.  I was not inside when
the fire suppression activated, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, not much of this matters once the datacenter gets to the point
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/xgarreau/status/1369559995491172354&quot;&gt;SGB2 just did&lt;/a&gt;.  Don’t worry, though!  That data center is still
&lt;a href=&quot;http://status.ovh.com/vms/index_sbg2.html&quot;&gt;green across the board according to its status page&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last week I wrote about an American English dialect.  Regional dialects are
incredibly common!  Another well known regional dialect is the…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-09</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-09</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/LNq9oMZNc8IINqOOlf/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I wrote about an American English dialect.  Regional dialects are
incredibly common!  Another well known regional dialect is the dialect from
Osaka, Japan and the surrounding regions - commonly known as the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kansai_dialect&quot;&gt;Kansai dialect, western Japanese, or “Kansai-ben”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kansai-ben is usually characterized as being a bit harsher to the ears but
more melodic.  All of Kansai dialect has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2718816&quot;&gt;an acestor in the Kinai dialect,&lt;/a&gt;
and was considered the national dialect of Japan while Kyoto was the capital.
However, once the capital moved to Edo - now Tokyo - the dialect of that
region took hold on the country, now commonly known as Tokyo dialect or
Standard Japanese.  However, using the Kansai dialect is often
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ndlonline.ndl.go.jp/#!/detail/R300000001-I000000007089-00&quot;&gt;a source of pride to people from Kansai&lt;/a&gt;, with many being rather attached
to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kansai-ben used to be the stereotypical villain but now it’s more commonly
associated with boisterous personalities in Japanese pop-culture.  Because of
the shared regional origins, the Kansai-ben is often associated with a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manzai&quot;&gt;Manzai&lt;/a&gt; comedy.  Manzai is a type of traditional Japanese stand-up comedy
based around a funny man (Tsukommi) and a straight man (Boke) - but more often
than not they’ll be speaking with a Kansai dialect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are grammatical differences, different words, and a few other differences
between Kansai dialect and Tokyo dialect.   The difference I think that’s
the most interesting is one that is often more difficult for English speakers:
Pitch Accent.  This is one of the quickest ways that non-Kansai dialect
speakers will identity Kansa dialect speakers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not an expert in pitch accent - far from it.  If you’re interested in
learning more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O6AoilGEers&quot;&gt;Pitch Accent, Dogen has a wonderful 10 minute video&lt;/a&gt;
but the trick to Standard Japanese intonation is to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G0ULPlBeKzg&quot;&gt;just say it flat.  Right?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time for me to butcher an example.  Let’s take “Japan” - &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ni-ho-n&lt;/code&gt;.
It has 3 mora - which isn’t quite a syllable but.. close enough.  For Tokyo
dialect, this starts out low pitch, raises, the lowers again.  This is called
the nakadaka (中高) pattern.  For Kansai dialect, though, we start the pitch
high, then are low for rest of the word - known as the atamadaka (頭高) pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the most important thing you need to know when about Kansai-ben when
visiting Osaka?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked:
「儲かりまっかぁ？」 (Mokari makka?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Respond with:
「ぼちぼちでんなぁー。たこ焼きとビールが必要や。」 (Bochi bochi, denna. Takoyaki to biru ga hitsuyoya.)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[I read a really interesting medium post by Piotr Migdal about
procrastination.  In particular, it reframes the issue of procratination
from…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-08</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-08</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l0HlC1bti6z8ceG9q/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read a really interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://pmigdal.medium.com/dont-fight-flight-or-freeze-your-body-and-emotions-96f5aa30b299&quot;&gt;medium post by Piotr Migdal&lt;/a&gt; about
procrastination.  In particular, it reframes the issue of procratination
from being a productivity problem into what else it could be: an
emotional management problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dont-delay/202003/negative-emotions-today-predict-procrastination-tomorrow&quot;&gt;Timothy Pychyl writes about this in Psychology Today&lt;/a&gt;  summarizing a few
studies.  We’re conditioned to not enjoy bad outcomes and often that is
exhibited by enacting our emotion-coping mechanisms -  fight, flight, or freeze.
Anxious about something?  Easy.  Just don’t do it.  Procrastination and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/dont-delay/200804/giving-in-feel-good-why-self-regulation-fails&quot;&gt;giving up a bit of self control is a form of mood repair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a bit of truth in there and it’s something good to introspect about.
Fight, flight, or freeze has been a part of our instinctual responses for a
long time.  It served us very well in the past and can today as well.  Flat out
rejecting this and fighting it as a time management issue may be burying other
problems and exacerbating it long term.  Some theories point at one cause of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/shouldstorm/202012/we-ve-got-depression-all-wrong-it-s-trying-save-us&quot;&gt;depression being another outlet of the freeze response&lt;/a&gt; - a biological
defense mechanism to trauma perceived by our autonomic nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introspection on how you’re feeling the next time you feel that need to get
away from it all (by cleaning or watching netflix) might be more effective than
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;tomato timers&lt;/a&gt; or to-do lists.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Google made a statement a few days ago that they’re
not building new ways to track individuals across the web for targeted ads. The optimist…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-05</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-05</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/3o85xB7Mortef8YksE/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google made a statement a few days ago that they’re
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/products/ads-commerce/a-more-privacy-first-web/&quot;&gt;not building new ways to track individuals across the web for targeted ads&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimist in me wants to say that they heard the message from
consumers that it’s not wanted, and that targeted ads just aren’t
making the money that they used to.  People are wisening up
and don’t click ads.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/01/06/1015784/adsense-google-surveillance-adnauseam-obfuscation/&quot;&gt;Or people are intentionally sending bad data.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The realist in me says they have something else, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/03/googles-floc-terrible-idea&quot;&gt;FLoC&lt;/a&gt;, that they’ve
shown works. Something even more privacy-invasive. Something that locks
competitors out. Something that is more predatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I have nothing to worry about. Google won’t be evil.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Cephalopod - squid, octopus, nautilus, and cuttlefish - are both adorable
and incredibly intelligent.  Within the first hour of their…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-04</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-04</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/F0OZbSrz7SsIRs2FYv/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cephalopod - squid, octopus, nautilus, and cuttlefish - are both adorable
and incredibly intelligent.  Within the first hour of their life, they
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wnet/nature/baby-cephalopods-first-moments-tzuuij/19380/&quot;&gt;start foraging and camoflauging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2020.3161&quot;&gt;Recent studies&lt;/a&gt; have shown that they also possess the capacity for
exerting self control.  This is commonly known as the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford_marshmallow_experiment&quot;&gt;Stanford marshmallow experiment&lt;/a&gt;, a study on delayed gratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does bring into question animal intelligence and conciousness.
Urbanization means people spend less time with other animals.  We interact
with a smaller variety of animals and thus can see much less varied expressions
of intelligence from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/wnet/nature/octopus-making-contact-preview-a98u9n/19851/&quot;&gt;Dr. David Scheel raised a Day Octopus in his home&lt;/a&gt;, documenting the
experience.  The Scheel family named her Heidi.  Heidi was able to show
recognition of faces, solved puzzles, and built relationships with members
of the Scheel family.  Of this, Scheel noted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am less intrigued by the differences and more interested in our
similarities. What kind of a connection is possible with an animal that has
three hearts and blue blood running through its veins? It’s been a privilege
to have a relationship with such a strange and wonderful creature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be that we aren’t smart enough to judge how smart animals are.
The Octopus followed a different evolutionary path than we did.  As such, the
expressions of intelligence they have could just be poorly understood by us.
Just because we excel in a larger number of areas on average doesn’t mean that
some animals can do better than some people in specific tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yro.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=191810&amp;#x26;cid=15757347&quot;&gt;From Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the 1980s, Yosemite National Park was having a serious problem
with bears: They would wander into campgrounds and break into the garbage
bins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This put both bears and people at risk. So the Park Service started
installing armored garbage cans that were tricky to open — you had to
swing a latch, align two bits of handle, that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it turns out it’s actually quite tricky to get the design of these cans
just right. Make it too complex and people can’t get them open to put away
their garbage in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Said one park ranger, “There is considerable overlap between the intelligence
of the smartest bears and the dumbest tourists.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the entire marshmallow test is flawed.  It purports that cuttlefish
show intelligence normally seen in toddlers.  Maybe cuttlefish are just able to
show intelligence in one aspect that is similar to toddlers.  Or maybe
cuttlefish aren’t that smart - &lt;a href=&quot;http://vaviper.blogspot.com/2019/06/from-onion-study-reveals-babies-are.html&quot;&gt;maybe babies are just stupid.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The “far right” social media platform, Gab, was
breached sometime last month and had public messages, private messages
and password hashes…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-03</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-03</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/3ov9jNziFTMfzSumAw/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “far right” social media platform, Gab, was
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2021/03/gab-the-far-right-website-has-been-hacked-and-70gb-of-data-leaked/&quot;&gt;breached sometime last month&lt;/a&gt; and had public messages, private messages
and password hashes leaked on March 1st.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s ignore the… uh… unprofessional (to put it lightly) statement the
founder made and how they responded to this event in general.  It’s not worth
unpacking all of that.  It really isn’t.  I promise you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, let’s chat about how this happened.  It’s pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site in question had &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.vn/oxbck&quot;&gt;a commit&lt;/a&gt; from the Gab CTO which migrated a
specific SQL query away from the library abstraction SQL and into raw SQL -
the query language used to interact more directly with their database.
This is often done because a custom SQL query can often be used to greatly
improve performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of this, they used string interpolation do craft the query.  String
interpolation is kinda like saying &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;VARIABLE_U&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;james&lt;/code&gt; and I want to
interpolate that into &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SELECT * FROM user WHERE username = &amp;#39;$VARIABLE_U&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt; so
that I end up with the final string of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SELECT * FROM WHERE username = &amp;#39;james&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way of crafting SQL can fail because of what is known as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://owasp.org/www-community/attacks/SQL_Injection&quot;&gt;SQL Injection&lt;/a&gt;. In our example, what if &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;VARIABLE_U&lt;/code&gt; was coming from an
input field on a website?  In that case, a user could type whatever they wanted
into that field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a user was to type in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&amp;#39; OR &amp;#39;a&amp;#39; = &amp;#39;a&lt;/code&gt;, the final string would then look
something like &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SELECT * FROM user WHERE username = &amp;#39;&amp;#39; OR &amp;#39;a&amp;#39; = &amp;#39;a&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;.
Instead of limiting to a single &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;username&lt;/code&gt; value, we’d instead retrieve any
users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be elaborated on to do even more - such as with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://owasp.org/www-community/attacks/Blind_SQL_Injection&quot;&gt;Blind SQL Injection&lt;/a&gt; techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How should they instead of handled this?  By using the library to “bind”
parameters.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveRecord/Querying.html#method-i-find_by_sql&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; supports this in the function used by the
change that caused the breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our example, we could instead write the query as
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SELECT * FROM user WHERE username = ?&lt;/code&gt; and then tell the library to bind
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;VARIABLE_U&lt;/code&gt; to the first numbered parameter.  No string interpolation would
be performed, and with most databases the query would be sent over completely
separate from the bound parameters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should have been caught in code review.  I mean.. if they do code
review, right?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Regional Dialects are something of an interesting topic for me.  It’s not just
an indicator of your originating geography but also the…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-02</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-02</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/5niBMBXRnhmlmMWCun/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regional Dialects are something of an interesting topic for me.  It’s not just
an indicator of your originating geography but also the cultural upbringing
you had.  Over the next few weeks I’ll be picking out a few different
language dialects to both learn about and write about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, a dialect that’s near and dear to me: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_English&quot;&gt;Appalachian English&lt;/a&gt;,
also known as Smoky Mountain English or Southern Mountain English.  This is
the dialect that’s most often attributed to the inland Southern United States
and has many features of 18th-century colonial English.  I’d often encounter
this dialect with my family in Kentucky, Tennessee, and West Viriginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the words I’ve picked up over time that I can think of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;afeared&lt;/code&gt; - to be afraid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;buggy&lt;/code&gt; - a shopping cart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;britches&lt;/code&gt; - pants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;crick&lt;/code&gt; - this may be either a stiffness of joints in the body or a creek&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;fixin&lt;/code&gt; - this can also be a few things - either to say something is soon to
happen, or a portion of food&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;holler&lt;/code&gt; - the steep valley between two hills, because you can “holler”
across to the other side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;plumb&lt;/code&gt; - completely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;reckon&lt;/code&gt; - suppose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;skifting&lt;/code&gt; - a dusting, usually of snow on the ground&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;sody-pop&lt;/code&gt; - carbonated beverages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;spell&lt;/code&gt; - either a duration of time or the state of being lightheaded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;yonder&lt;/code&gt; - somewhere distant, away from where we are currently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appalachian English has many other archaic phrases, words, and prefixes.&lt;br&gt;
Most of the above fall into that - either from older English words like
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;breetches&lt;/code&gt; or the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;a-&lt;/code&gt; (such as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;afeared&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;a-haunted&lt;/code&gt;) prefix which comes
from Early Middle English.  &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;right&lt;/code&gt; can also be used with adjectives and
adverbs such as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;right fine&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;right quick&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southern drawl is also an important aspect of this dialect.  Sourthern Drawl -
considered &lt;a href=&quot;http://dialectblog.com/2011/04/20/twangs-vs-drawls/&quot;&gt;different from the Southern twang&lt;/a&gt; - is a common
pattern in how the vowels are prolonged making the speech sound slower.
To many, this leads to the incorrect assumption that
an individual with a drawl is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/why-does-a-southern-drawl-sound-uneducated-to-some/&quot;&gt;uneducated or dim-witted&lt;/a&gt;.
Part of this is from a lack of exposure to Southern accents - people that
don’t hear it can immediately hear the other-ness.  However, even people that
grow up with the accent are told that a Southern accent is “wrong” via
pop-culture and media.  How many celebrities speak with a Southern drawl?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dialects like this might sound strange to people that aren’t part of them.
However, to those that are within that dialect outsiders without it sound
foreign.  To quote my cousins in regards to my differing dialect,
“Yew talk real funny!  Y’all spake all fast-like.  Yer a yankee from up
yonder, aintcha?”&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Social engineering is one of the most difficult attack vectors to detect.  It’s
also one of the oldest technqiues in the espionage handbook…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-03-01</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-03-01</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/1gRtl9mdLQvvvOfR9u/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social engineering is one of the most difficult attack vectors to detect.  It’s
also one of the oldest technqiues in the espionage handbook.  Most of the time
in this day and age it’s implemented as spear-phishing or in other ways via
email.  That’s when you aren’t dealing with highly motivated nation-state
actors where money and time becomes less of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s think like a threat actor for a moment.  Who’s going to look the most
threatening to an employee?  The other, of course.  Someone outside the company.
That’s why spear-phishing can be so successful - you purport to be someone
trusted.  Someone that’s a part of the company.  However, that leaves tech in
the way.  That makes it easier to detect, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So then.. let’s pivot.  How can we become someone trustworthy?  Well… What
if we only needed to fool one employee - someone that wouldn’t expect it -
and use that to get a foot-hold?  How about.. HR.  HR gets a candidate.  On
paper, they’re perfect.  They came from top schools, they know your stack,
the teams that interview them are gung-ho, their references are all gushing
about how amazing this individual is.  And that’s exactly how we get someone
on the inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound too outlandish?  It has happened many times - even in recent years.
Alexey Karetnikov had joined Microsoft as a QA engineer in 2010.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2010/07/who-was-the-12th-russian-spy-at-microsoft/344876/&quot;&gt;It was purported that he was there to capture intelligence&lt;/a&gt; for the Russian
intelligence agencies.  He was on the sloppier side and was tracked by the
US intelligence agencies as soon as he set foot in the US.  He was deported
over charges of immigration violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fbi.gov/news/speeches/responding-effectively-to-the-chinese-economic-espionage-threat&quot;&gt;The current FBI Director, Christopher Wray, spoke about this as well.&lt;/a&gt;
In 2020, the Boston FBI field office arrested a researcher that was smuggling
vials of biological research back to the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone’s as motivated as these folks are and have the backing of a
nation state nearly anything is possible.  These are just the cases we hear
about, too.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Barsky&quot;&gt;Jack Barsky&lt;/a&gt; is a more famous example of someone that had
been a spy for the KGB in New York City for 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In espionage, reality is often more outlandish than even fiction.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There are people that claim they can tell you where water is via a dowsing rod.
Water finding.  Water witching.  Water Divination.  I’m…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-26</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-26</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/S1N2zUokK7jiM/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are people that claim they can tell you where water is via a dowsing rod.
Water finding.  Water witching.  Water Divination.  I’m gonna spoil it for you:
it’s hogwash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dowsing&quot;&gt;Dowsing&lt;/a&gt; has been a pseudoscience employed since the 1500s, and it was
just as useless then as it is now.  Traditionally the way it works is that
you take  a forked twig, hold it in front of you, and it’ll make small
movements towards what you’re trying to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small movements are said to be magnetic ion something something by
divinators.  Those small movements are known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ideomotor_phenomenon&quot;&gt;Ideomotor phenomenon&lt;/a&gt;.
It’s where a mental image or a thought bring on a reflexive muscular action
outside of conscious knowledge.  It’s the same effect that you’ll see with
other “precognition-lite” techniques like Ouija boards, automatic writing, and
facilitated communication.  (Sorry if I’ve dunked on your preferred
pseudoscience, happy for you to tell me how I’m wrong.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been tested again and again and show that it’s a whole bunch of baloney.
While the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificexploration.org/docs/9/jse_09_1_betz.pdf&quot;&gt;1990 study by Hans-Dieter Betz&lt;/a&gt; concludes that it works,
but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Water-dowsing%3A-TheScheunen-experiments-Enright/a51593dc28ad8c03eb51c2eb6d9e1d0d7db19ed4&quot;&gt;statistical analysis by J. T. Enright in 1995&lt;/a&gt; finds that
out of 500 dowsers even the best of the best were about only 0.4% better than
random chance which could be easily attributed to statistical fluctuation.
That’s the most POSITIVE study I can find on it; there’s countless others that
call out dowsing as completely fake. Algeria 1943, New Zealand 1948, Britain
1959, the British Ministry of Defense did one in 1971 - the list goes on and
every single one of them show this as a complete farce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sallylepage.medium.com/in-2017-uk-water-companies-still-rely-on-magic-6eb62e036b02&quot;&gt;water dowsing is employed by ten out of the twelve&lt;/a&gt;
water companies in the UK.  Dowsing is considered “tried-and-tested” methods
of finding water by these companies, if
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stwater/status/932618829976481792&quot;&gt;Twitter is to be believed&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/YorkshireWater/status/932650378260307969&quot;&gt;Really.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ADE_651&quot;&gt;ADE 651&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GT200&quot;&gt;GT200&lt;/a&gt; are modern versions of the dowsing rod being sold
in military applications as late as 2011 and have been found just as effective
as previous dowsing rods.  Read: They’re as good as random chance because
that’s all it is.  They say they can track drugs, bombs, ivory, and who knows
what else.  What’s even more amazing is they’re purported to be powered by the
user’s static electricity and they have programmable cards that you have to pay
extra for because of.. electrostatic magnetic ion … It’s a huge fake and by
2010 companies of both swindled people out of millions and millions of dollars.
This includes the governments of the USA, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.vn/20130505091113/http://www.thisissomerset.co.uk/Bomb-detector-kit-boss-court-face-fraud-charges/story-16522530-detail/story.html&quot;&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/04/world/middleeast/04sensors.html&quot;&gt;Iraq&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.today/20130505142849/http://www.thisissomerset.co.uk/paid-46-000-unfit-bomb-detectors-court-told/story-18482857-detail/story.html&quot;&gt;Lebanon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bangkokpost.com/thailand/general/1555810/man-jailed-over-fake-bomb-detector-fraud&quot;&gt;Thailand&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20110722224740/http://rotativo.com.mx/seguridad/con-detector-molecular-sedena-asegura-arsenal-y-dinero/24719/html/&quot;&gt;Mexico&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The creators of these devices are currently being litigated so thoroughly that
they’ll need a dowsing rod to find themselves out of the mess they’re in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thing is - if you have other sensory cues, you use your mind, and with the
observer expectancy cognitive bias - dowsing really works!  At least, it works
about as well as me going out into that same field and rolling a D20.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[In the before times, two titans battled out a war in North America - a bitter
ande drawn out war that waged on for decades. Eventually, the…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-25</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-25</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/yugSj8GSC0wXm/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the before times, two titans battled out a war in North America - a bitter
ande drawn out war that waged on for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VHS&quot;&gt;Video Home System&lt;/a&gt; overcame the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betamax&quot;&gt;Betamax&lt;/a&gt; cassette.
Home Video consumption became a norm.  The Videocassette Recorder was
feared by the television industry and heralded by consumers.
A new way to consume movies and television was born with the VHS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was one issue with translating theatrical movies to the small screen:
Home televisions were 4:3 aspect ratio.  This meant that the the screens had
a width of 1.33 times the height unlike the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CinemaScope&quot;&gt;Cinemascope&lt;/a&gt; and other
Widescreen formats for theatrical releases that became popular after 1960.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two techniques are available to make the widescreen theatrical releases
fit on a smaller screen.  There’s always letterboxing - which adds black bars
above and below the screen.  Another technique is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan_and_scan&quot;&gt;Pan and Scan&lt;/a&gt; - where
the image is translated to better show off the points of interest in the
cinematography, shaping the film to match the 4:3 through cropping or other
techniques.  This would be done by an editor and could drastically change
the tone of a scene if done poorly.  This is why many criticize and refuse
to release a pan and scan version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kind of film that would do well in the “home cinema” also differed
from what would do well in the theater. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the the theater there is less need to keep the audience’s attention -
they were stuck there in the building.  At home, you have distractions so a
different kind of movie can prosper.  Comedy movies like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mallrats&quot;&gt;Mallrats&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Lebowski&quot;&gt;The Big Lebowski&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_Space&quot;&gt;Office Space&lt;/a&gt; did ABYSMALLY in the theater but
found their footing once they were released on VHS.  Some of this is
attributed to the fact that they can be enjoyed more recreationally and
sporadically than many other movies that require direct attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Horror film genre &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Thing_(1982_film)&quot;&gt;The Thing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Abyss&quot;&gt;The Abyss&lt;/a&gt;, and “slasher” movies like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halloween_(1978_film)&quot;&gt;Halloween&lt;/a&gt; did extraorgdinarily well on VHS.  This could because.. what’s
scarier than when the monster is.. inside your own house?  On the small screen
it’s harder to see what’s going on but sometimes that adds to the fear.. plus,
you can’t see the zipper so easily on the scary demon monster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also some films that wouldn’t be as popular today if it weren’t for
home video - such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labyrinth_(1986_film)&quot;&gt;Labyrinth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blade_Runner&quot;&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/a&gt;,
or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Trouble_in_Little_China&quot;&gt;Big Trouble in Little China&lt;/a&gt;.  These three did not do well in the box
office but sold well on home video.  A good thing, too - they’re all fantastic
films and it’s a good thing they weren’t forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VHS may be gone - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/brittanyhodak/2016/07/23/rip-vhs-worlds-last-vcr-to-be-made-this-month/?sh=4ec4c88623da&quot;&gt;the last VCR was produced in 2016&lt;/a&gt; - but it’s
still in our collective pop-culture memory.  You get the same gritty effects
used all over videos online - giving a bit of realism that it’s a “found”
tape.  There’s even an anthology Horror series called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/V/H/S&quot;&gt;V/H/S&lt;/a&gt; which uses the
the look of VHS tapes to hide all of the imperfections of CGI to great effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself?  I just remember the joy of being able to watch Star Wars
in the warmth of my pajamas on Saturday while eating some cereal.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Having not gone to any conferences, conventions, or the like for a while
a quora post caught my eye being shared in discord. A ways back I’d…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-24</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-24</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/OOT9daJDqqFdtMb1vq/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having not gone to any conferences, conventions, or the like for a while
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/In-Silicon-Valley-is-company-swag-a-status-symbol&quot;&gt;a quora post caught my eye being shared in discord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ways back I’d have collected all the swag I could.  Heck, I only wore shirts
that were swag because they were free.  It was great because I wouldn’t have
to pay for them and they were decently high quality! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now a days, I don’t really want that stuff.  The last conference I went to I even
won a new computer monitor (thanks, I guess, Asus?) which I promptly gave
to a friend because I already have a monitor and didn’t want to bring it back
on a train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting swag can be exciting - except for when I have 10 venmo hoodies, 4 Wayfair
hoodies, 2 jackets that are branded elsewhere, and now more socks than I know what
to do with.  It’s just not much of a marketing channel for me anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say that - but then came the time when I spoke with the Pokemon Company.
They give out nice shirts that were exclusive, high quality, and from a brand that
I have an affinity for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, exclusive, high quality, and engaging brands.  They don’t really even
need to market to me, but do.  So why is it that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fastcompany.com/90260185/its-time-to-stop-spending-billions-on-cheap-conference-swag&quot;&gt;companies spend billions&lt;/a&gt;
on low quality garbage to give out at conferences?  Do we need more
tiny and useless thumb drives, pop-sockets, or totes?  (They shouldn’t.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For companies giving out swag to employees there’s now entire companies devoted
to creating these - like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swagup.com/&quot;&gt;SwagUp&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a little more interesting as
an employee but…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d rather just get snacks, experiences, or other things that I can
consume rather than more things that’ll probably end up in a landfill.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The ongoing pandemic has led to everyone feeling a little disconnected
from one-another.  It’s no surprise that we crave human interaction…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-23</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-23</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/cQciLRtfbXKeI/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ongoing pandemic has led to everyone feeling a little disconnected
from one-another.  It’s no surprise that we crave human interaction
when we can’t see one another!  However, Zoom just feels too… meeting-ish.
Communities don’t really form around Zoom.  I think that’s why folks are
turning to more “video game”-like aspects to break the physical distances
between us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we’re meeting in person, we’re usually limited by physics.  This is
something we’re really used to.  You can only have so many people in a room,
you can’t really hear folks outside of a short distance away, and you know
when someone is talking to you because they are usually giving you their
attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So - simulating those physical limitations has been seen in a few products
(games?  tools?  communication devices?) that’ve been dropping.  I’d first
seen something like this at the Recurse Center - they have Virtual RC &amp;#x26; it’s
really neat!  It’s like being in the RC space but you’re represented by just
a little avatar version of your face.  I think there’s a few other ways that
this can work - and products show that’s the case as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waxy.org/2021/02/announcing-skittish/&quot;&gt;Skittish&lt;/a&gt; is one of these - and I saw it on the front page of Hacker
News.  You get an avatar that’s a Raccoon or an Owl or a snake - and you
hang out in a virtual space, watch videos together, all that.  It’s neat,
but definitely limited in what it can do. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gather.town/&quot;&gt;Gather.town&lt;/a&gt; is a bit older, and if I remember correctly had Pokemon
sprites to begin with, way back.  A few college students tossed it together
and put it up online &amp;#x26; it grew like wildfire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go a bit more realistic, there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hubs.mozilla.com/&quot;&gt;Hub by Mozilla&lt;/a&gt;.  This is available
via VR and feels much more video-gamey than the others.  You can easily modify
the space you’re in and customize it together with other people.  I’ve seen
a number of other examples like this - the closest being Rec Room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s still &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.connect.secondlife.com/about&quot;&gt;Second Life&lt;/a&gt; and Second Life has been around.. forever.
Thing is… Second Life gets weird.  Real weird.  Let’s not think about that
too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there’s always a want for Human connection, though.  It doesn’t even
have to be instant.  Sometimes you just want to listen to some chilled out
music and write letters to people via a deer postman.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1070710/Kind_Words_lo_fi_chill_beats_to_write_to/&quot;&gt;Kind Words (lo fi chill beats to write to)&lt;/a&gt; gives you that experience.
Kind Words is about writing nice letters and reading nice letters from other
people.  It makes you feel much better inside than many other interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest?  I think we need less Zoom and we need more Kind Words
in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There were two posts on the front page of Hacker News yesterday -
Choose Boring Technology and Choose Exciting Technology.
Both make are…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-22</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-22</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/2A0jXvUa3KOufBYT53/giphy-downsized.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two posts on the front page of Hacker News yesterday -
&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26211721&quot;&gt;Choose Boring Technology&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26212563&quot;&gt;Choose Exciting Technology&lt;/a&gt;.
Both make are great points and are compelling on their own, but they’re
completely at odds with one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boring Technology gives examples like PHP, Postgres, Java, and all other
sorts of technology that’s been around for a while and is.. well.. not as
new and shiny.  Battle-tested technology.  Things that everyone on the team
knows.  The argument for boring technology is generally that you won’t
get anything that surprises you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exciting Technology is … uh.. okay, so bear with me: the examples given
are Cassandra (at least 12 years old), MongoDB (&gt;11 years),
Clojure (&gt;14 years), and NodeJS (..let’s not touch that).  For the sake of
simplicity, let’s say Exciting Technology is technology that an
engineer is less familiar with and as such cannot for certain say
that it will solve the issues they currently have - but there are
some shiny new features that they really like!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s … not talk touch on my personal experiences with Cassandra, Mongo,
and the like.  Let’s not touch on the issues that seemed to be the case
at Etsy’s SRE &amp;#x26; maintenance of servers.  Let’s not even touch on all the
fighting going on in the HN comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I think it’s interesting to talk about the kinds of people
that do this because I don’t think that either of these articles will
change people’s minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Humans-Humorous-Software-Engineering-dp-1484221575/dp/1484221575/ref=dp_ob_title_bk&quot;&gt;Managing Humans by Michael Lopp&lt;/a&gt; is a book that’s not just about
managing humans.  In it he writes about engineering culture, different
personalities you might find, and communication skills.  Things that are
sometimes considered tangential to management (but are very important!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapter “Stables and Volatiles” details two archetypes that you’ll
commonly see within engineering cultures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stables are engineers that happily work within a set of confines - even
appreciating these confines such as direction and deadlines.  They assess
risk, carefully mitigate failure, and aim for predictable outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volatiles will show up, stomp on everything that exists, and leave a trail
of disruption in their wake.  However, when they build.. they sure build a LOT.
In some cases, what they make will be novel and would not have occurred
otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stables and Volatiles are at odds with one another.  They do not get along
on everything but a team with both can be incredibly successful - even if
there’s a bit of conflict along the way.  Volatiles become stables,
and sometime stables become volatiles, and neither is really good or bad.
They just &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These archetypes are applicable to the argument about boring versus exciting
technology.  Stables will more likely than not choose the familiar.
Volatiles will sometimes choose the foreign.  Neither is right or wrong -
at least not intrinsically.  Instead, it’s gotta be a balance and you’ve
got to use the right tool for the right job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you lean too far towards boring technology nothing will be pushed forward.
If you lean too far towards the exciting you’ll end up with a backend written
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.little-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Little&lt;/a&gt; using a home-grown &lt;a href=&quot;https://dfithian.github.io/2021/02/15/database-implementation-part-1.html&quot;&gt;database written in Haskell&lt;/a&gt;.  That..
does sound pretty exciting, though, doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s a nifty new Electron alternative called Tauri which purports
to be more memory efficient than Electron!  Competition is awesome…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-20</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-20</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/FPjbHO0jJxGsE/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a nifty new Electron alternative called &lt;a href=&quot;https://tauri.studio/&quot;&gt;Tauri&lt;/a&gt; which purports
to be more memory efficient than Electron!  Competition is awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tauri is written in Rust and &lt;a href=&quot;https://tauri.studio/en/docs/getting-started/technical-details#user-interface&quot;&gt;utilizes a webview instead of bundling&lt;/a&gt;
the entire Chrome browser within it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a webview isn’t a particularly new idea - &lt;a href=&quot;https://deskgap.com/&quot;&gt;DeskGap&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pojala/electrino&quot;&gt;Electrino&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/neutralinojs/neutralinojs&quot;&gt;Neutralino&lt;/a&gt;, and others.  On Linux, this works pretty okay!  You get a
webkit rendering engine (of an unknown version).  On MacOS you get
the Safari flavor of webkit.  On Windows 7 you often get IE11 which..
yikes.  Then on earlier Windows 10 you get the old non-Webkit Edge,
newer versions mostly get Webkit Edge.  It’s.. a little all over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing that Electron brings is that you know exactly what version
of Webkit you’re building against and can cut down on the pain you
feel when testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing is that Electron has a lot of batteries already included
and while Tauri has a lot of features in the works - they just aren’t
there yet!  However, the roadmap looks great and who knows -
maybe it’d really hit that right balance between performance
and features without having to write a native app version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dunno, though, I feel that Electron being resource hungry isn’t the
end of the world.  For the most part, you can cut down on memory in
Electron in the same way you would a standard web app on Chrome -
through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.electronjs.org/docs/tutorial/performance&quot;&gt;profiling and optimization&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Perseverance rover confirmed a successful touchdown yesterday,
February 19th at ~3:55PM EST.  The mission is one of the most ambitious…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-19</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-19</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;img src=&apos;https://media.giphy.com/media/nT8678QggafnBb5g8I/giphy.gif&apos; alt=&apos;null&apos; loading=&apos;lazy&apos; /&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Perseverance rover confirmed a successful touchdown yesterday,
February 19th at ~3:55PM EST.  The mission is one of the most ambitious
we’ve sent to the red planet - but not just because of the rover
(which, itself, is the most complex and featured rover we’ve sent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EDL (Entry, Descent, and Landing) platform was also for more advanced
than any other we’d sent - with the descent into the Martian atmosphere
being yet another part of the experiment.  The ablative heat shielding
covered the bottom of the capsule - with a type of plating covering it
which upon heating would vaporize and be carried away from the
Perseverance capsule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Perseverance also carried 661lbs of tungsten weights.  However, just
because they’re dead weight doesn’t mean they won’t serve a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two 165 pound blocks of tungsten kept Perseverance in a stable and balanced
spin on its journey from Earth.  This prevented any one side of the capsule
from getting too hot.  These are jettisoned 900 miles or so above Mars as
they’d no longer be needed.  Waste not, though.  These two tungsten blocks
will slam into the surface of Mars at 9,000 mph or so and is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/17/science/nasa-mars-landing.html&quot;&gt;part of a very vital experiment&lt;/a&gt;.  The InSight lander has a
seismometer and even at 2000 miles away it’ll be listening for Perseverance
knocking with these tungsten payloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removing those two tungsten blocks is an important part of the entry phase
because while balance is required during the journey, the entry requires
debalancing.  Because one side of the capsule is heavier than the other
the entry angle will be at 16°.  This leads to a slight amount of lift
experienced by the craft, allowing the descent to be controlled via
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reaction_control_system&quot;&gt;RCS (Reaction Control System)&lt;/a&gt; powered rotation - rotate left to
cause the lift to push you one way, right to push the other, and go left
and right consistently to burn off speed.  This is all autonomous!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also six 55lb tungsten masses that ensure landing is aligned.
These are jettisoned right before firing the parachute and are used to
ensure that the radar will be oriented in the correct direction.  While
the RCS was fired roughly 2,256 times during atmosphere entry, at this point
they aren’t a whole lot of use.  These tungsten blocks are jettisoned two at
a time, and will cause the craft to roll into the exact orientation needed
for the rest of the descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haven’t heard yet if InSight heard Perseverance’s hello to start a welcome
party, but all of this was fantastically interesting to me and I’m always
surprised at how much NASA can achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wanna watch it?  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/videos/919215638&quot;&gt;They streamed the landing on twitch!&lt;/a&gt;
What an amazing future we live in.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[In 2019, the World Health Organization recognized burnout as an occupational phenomenon in the ICD-11.
However, a relatively new article by…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-18</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-18</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;img src=&apos;https://media.giphy.com/media/cVWZ8dVs5VOEvdhH1M/giphy.gif&apos; alt=&apos;null&apos; loading=&apos;lazy&apos; /&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the World Health Organization &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news/item/28-05-2019-burn-out-an-occupational-phenomenon-international-classification-of-diseases&quot;&gt;recognized burnout as an occupational phenomenon in the ICD-11&lt;/a&gt;.
However, a relatively new &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2021/02/beyond-burned-out&quot;&gt;article by HBR about burnout points at studies&lt;/a&gt; that show the pandemic has
been causing burnout to run rampant since early 2020.  “Knowledge workers” are now mostly working remotely -
looking at Zoom, for example, they went from 10 million to 200 million active users effectively overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify: Burnout is really just another term for chronic stress causing emotional, mental, and even physical damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of companies just look at it as a personal problem.  Get better at self-care, do some yoga, use those new-fangled
meditation apps.  Those might help soothe some of the pains caused by chronic stress, but they don’t get to the
actual causes of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/246546370_Making_a_significant_difference_with_burnout_interventions_Researcher_and_practitioner_collaboration&quot;&gt;A 2012 Study by Christina Maslach, Michael Leither and Susan Jackson&lt;/a&gt; point at the causes
of burnout to be more organizational than personal.  The top cause?  Unsustainable workload.  Also in there
is the lack of a supportive community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a look over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w27612&quot;&gt;NBER’s working paper on the impact of COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; - what do you see?
Remote workers on average work 10% more during all of this.  People also have more shorter meetings than ever
before.  You end up with a heavier workload and sparser, shorter action-oriented meetings - without the same
affordances given to social interactions unrelated to the work at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HBR article I’d linked above did a survey of 1500 workers - and found that nearly 90% said that their
work life was getting worse, more than half said their work was becoming more demanding, and half felt that
they couldn’t maintain a strong connection with their friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t really a new phenomenon, either.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1067175527180513280?lang=en&quot;&gt;Some CEOs of public companies have been pushing for 80
hours a week of work&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/carolineodonovan/how-ubers-hard-charging-corporate-culture-left-employees&quot;&gt;Uber’s employees were effectively not sleeping&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/08/16/technology/inside-amazon-wrestling-big-ideas-in-a-bruising-workplace.html&quot;&gt;Amazon worked people to exhaustion on Easter Sunday and Thanksgiving weekend&lt;/a&gt;, and if you
want to hear me go off about even my personal experience, just ask me about Venmo’s practices.
The superbowl “war room” that literally means being in the office for 24 hours without sleep is
just the tip of that iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, though - what I’m trying to say is that burnout is very real, very scary, and it’s gotta get
addressed sometime.  I don’t think that time is now, but it’s gotta be soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/research-rheingans-digital-enablers-five-hour-workday-productivity&quot;&gt;Maybe the 5 hour work day could become the norm&lt;/a&gt;.  I doubt it though.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Having lived in Texas for a few years I know a number of Texans right now that
have not had power for nearly 48 hours with freezing causing…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-17</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-17</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;img src=&apos;https://media.giphy.com/media/S5i0xeZEzcescmDFaq/giphy-downsized.gif&apos; alt=&apos;null&apos; loading=&apos;lazy&apos; /&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having lived in Texas for a few years I know a number of Texans right now that
have not had power for nearly 48 hours with freezing causing a real terrible
situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of this is caused because &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.texastribune.org/2011/02/08/texplainer-why-does-texas-have-its-own-power-grid/&quot;&gt;Texas has an isolated power grid&lt;/a&gt; with 3
interconnects to other states and 3 to Mexico - through what is known as ERCOT.
ERCOT was founded in 1970 and covers most of Texas.  Much of this was fueled by
a secessionist attitude many Texas lawmakers take, as well as a want to avoid
federal regulations.  A push to deregulate even more was in the late 90s and
much of ERCOT is powered by an aging and neglected coal and natural gas
infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a number of talking points saying that this is all because renewable
energy such as wind and solar are failing Texas - which isn’t the case.
Not only do modern wind turbines handle ice and snow through
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/scottcarpenter/2021/02/16/why-wind-turbines-in-cold-climates-dont-freeze-de-icing-and-carbon-fiber/&quot;&gt;some neat mechanisms&lt;/a&gt;, most of the 80% power deficit has to do with the
[natural gas, coal, and nuclear losing capacity]23.  Natural gas pipelines froze, coal
couldn’t be shipped, and nuclear plants did not have the abilities to
prevent the cooling water reservoirs from potentially freezing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all ends up hurting the citizens of Texas - where rolling power outages
turning into several day outages as ERCOT scrambles to make up for the
shortages.  Folks are cold, hungry, and don’t have water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a bad situation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Have you ever wanted to make an interface for a program, but
realized web just isn’t for you?  Don’t want to delve into
the madness and…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-16</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-16</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/LcfBYS8BKhCvK/giphy.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wanted to make an interface for a program, but
realized web just isn’t for you?  Don’t want to delve into
the madness and incantations needed to utilize &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ncurses&quot;&gt;new curses&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.willmcgugan.com/blog/tech/post/building-rich-terminal-dashboards/&quot;&gt;new blog post by Will McGugan&lt;/a&gt; about his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/willmcgugan/rich&quot;&gt;Python library Rich&lt;/a&gt;,
used to create beautiful CLIs.  The blog post details some basic
creation of dashboards using the various APIs available through Rich.
Having written a few things with ncurses, I can safely say that this
is a much more pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about folks over in javascript land?  Heck, while I love
Python I also adore Javascript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/@blessed/neo-blessed&quot;&gt;blessed&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/@blessed/blessed-contrib&quot;&gt;blessed-contrib&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/react-blessed&quot;&gt;react-blessed&lt;/a&gt;.  Blessed is a
Javascript library to create CLIs, but you’ll notice that the react API
it has is really game changing.  Using a special &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;blessed&lt;/code&gt; renderer in React
you can create CLI interfaces with the same paradigms as any React 16
application.  Combine that with the contrib package and you can have real
time terminal dashboards that show graphs, maps, spark lines, markdown,
and even picture rendering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to show off your cool new graphical web app.  It’s another
entirely to show off your 100% hacker terminal app.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[In Javascript, functions always have variadic arguments.  This leads to
some performance hits because there always has to be an adapter when…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-15</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-15</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;img src=&apos;https://media.giphy.com/media/3oriNYQX2lC6dfW2Ji/giphy.gif&apos; alt=&apos;null&apos; loading=&apos;lazy&apos; /&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Javascript, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Variadic_function&quot;&gt;functions always have variadic arguments&lt;/a&gt;.  This leads to
some performance hits because there always has to be an adapter when
using a JIT compilation.  The adapter required creating a new frame
in-between the caller and callee frames.
Creating a frame is super costly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the v8 development website a &lt;a href=&quot;https://v8.dev/blog/adaptor-frame&quot;&gt;new blog entry was posted&lt;/a&gt; which details
how this process works and what they’ve done to dramatically improve
function calls by optimizing this javascript feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How’d they solve it?  They work through the arguments array backwards
so they don’t really need to know how many arguments are in the stack,
but they can assume that there’s at least the enough arguments to
satisfy the parameter count - even if the arguments are &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;undefined&lt;/code&gt;.
This allows for cutting up the formal parameters and the extra variadic
arguments to pass them to the callee frame in a way that doesn’t require
extra lookups or an extra frame that will calculate it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No more overhead!  Super fast!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s something about the fact that I’m taking an at-home class for cooking
from a world-renowned french cuisine Chef that’s feeling like…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/2021-02-11</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/2021-02-11</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;
            &lt;img src=&apos;https://media.giphy.com/media/demgpwJ6rs2DS/giphy.gif&apos; alt=&apos;null&apos; loading=&apos;lazy&apos; /&gt;
          &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s something about the fact that I’m taking an at-home class for cooking
from a world-renowned french cuisine Chef that’s feeling like got an
uncomfortable “rich people things” vibe to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes me think about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/culture/kitchen-notes/the-joylessness-of-cooking&quot;&gt;a New Yorker article about the “Joylessness of Cooking”&lt;/a&gt;.
In theory, I love to cook.  It’s a way of peering through time and culture to see
how different people live and have lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those of us that still have stable incomes can often find far more ingredients
than ever before.  In New York City there’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://chefcollectivenyc.com/&quot;&gt;Chef Collective&lt;/a&gt; seeing even better
stock because many restaurants have shuttered or are generally seeing fewer
customers.  Some restaurants, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.xianfoods.com/&quot;&gt;Xi’an Famous Foods&lt;/a&gt;, have even pivoted to
selling “kits” instead of doing delivery because their foods don’t work well
with delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article points out a book - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Cook-Wolf-M-F-K-Fisher/dp/0865473366/&quot;&gt;How to Cook a Wolf by MFK Fisher&lt;/a&gt;.  The book
through dealing with shortages and difficulties that existed when cooking during
World War 2.  I am so grateful that my life is in a place where the feeling
of hunger is a choice rather than a fact of life.  I picked up a copy of the
book.  I’m really looking forward to reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, I love to cook.  In practice, I’ve been cooking far too often to
truly enjoy it.  I have always had an extreme respect for my mother and father.
We cooked food at home every single day while I was growing up - sometimes
out of necessity.  We didn’t do fast food, and we very rarely ate at
restaurants or had takeout.  They followed through with that to make sure
there was food on the table &amp;#x26; dealt with getting children to eat that food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really do love cooking - just.. in theory.  In practice, I can’t wait to
make it an exciting optional activity like this cooking class I’m taking.
I’ve registered to the wait list for the vaccine and boy am I looking forward
to that.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Team Kick Start]]></title><description><![CDATA[Joining a new team can be difficult.  You lack institutional knowledge and the
lingua franca that the rest of the team has - it’s like they’re speaking a language
you know at face value but the context tying it together is missing.]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/new-team-kick-start</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/new-team-kick-start</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Joining a new team can be difficult.  You lack institutional knowledge and the
lingua franca that the rest of the team has - it’s like they’re speaking a language
you know at face value but the context tying it together is missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- end-excerpt --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Seek first to understand, then to be understood.” - Habit 5: The 7 Habits of
highly Effective People&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we join a new team we want to have an impact right away.  Even with good
intent this can be disastrous without the right context.  There’s an approach
to this problem I found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190314125923/http://boz.com/articles/career-cold-start.html&quot;&gt;Andrew Bosworth’s site&lt;/a&gt;.  It
helps you quickly gather context and build a framework to base the knowledge
around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach starts with an agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-agenda&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-agenda&quot; aria-label=&quot;the agenda permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;25 minutes total.  3 questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 minutes: “Tell me everything you think I should know.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 minutes: “What are the biggest challenges the team has right now?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 minutes: “Who else should I speak with?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring a notebook, write everything down, only interrupt if you need
clarification,and repeat this process for every name you get.  If you don’t
know where to start, go to your manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tell-me-everything-you-think-i-should-know&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tell-me-everything-you-think-i-should-know&quot; aria-label=&quot;tell me everything you think i should know permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tell me everything you think I should know.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is intentionally vague.  The responses you get vary from person to person.
Just roll with it.  Keep taking notes, and only interrupt for clarification -
such as a term you don’t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture of the build system?  Ranting about their manager?  Favorite
restaurant in town?  All of this is great.  Why?  Because you’re learning
something new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people expect the universe to be efficient and orderly.  It isn’t.
Always assume everyone has something to teach you - even when talking about
topics that appear to bring no substantive value to the conversation or the
business needs.  People and organizations are messy so you’ll never know when
something is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won’t learn everything you’ll need to know with your new team.  Not by a long
shot.  Don’t fret - it’s OK.  There’s not nearly enough time for that in these
meetings.  Learning in depth will take you much, much longer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, this exercise helps you build rapport and context.  Sometimes you’ll
find the location of important documentation.  Other times you’ll gather
important tribal knowledge that’s not documented anywhere.  Then again, maybe
you’ll get a bit of a history lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this you can learn the common language of the team.  You’ll start by
building out a framework to understand where your context has gaps.  This is
where all the clarification comes in.  You gain knowledge that fills in those
gaps so you can hop over the many barriers that prevent you from joining
discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-the-biggest-challenges-the-team-has-right-now&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-are-the-biggest-challenges-the-team-has-right-now&quot; aria-label=&quot;what are the biggest challenges the team has right now permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What are the biggest challenges the team has right now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the first question this could be redundant - folks will pretty frequently
answer it partially as what you need to know.  That’s not important, ask
it anyway.  This question ensures that there is a focused time to understand
the perceived challenges that the team faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internalize the bigger problems - the problems that will take a long time to
fix.  “We’re using an outdated tech stack” or “We aren’t focused on building
the primary product”.  Maybe they’re complex, maybe systemic, but they won’t
be mitigated right away.  If you’re in a  leadership role, identify how the
team could move toward these as long term goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smaller problems are often small enough that the team hasn’t prioritized
them.  They might be quality of life improvements, or solvable issues with
process.  Things like “We’re overwhelmed with meetings” or “We have a flakey
test in the build that’s been frustrating”.  These are good to dig into so you
get some quick wins while building your knowledge of the systems at play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asynchronously follow up on these if you don’t understand them.  You don’t have
much time during the meeting, and once you know of its existence you should be
able to describe it in an email or slack message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-else-should-i-speak-with&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#who-else-should-i-speak-with&quot; aria-label=&quot;who else should i speak with permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Who else should I speak with?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question is incredibly important.  Sure, it helps you fan out into the
team.  At the same time, though, it builds a graph of influence via the
frequency of names.  Forget what they shared to you the first day.  This is
the true org chart to guide you through social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until you’ve run out of steam I would suggest following up with every name you
get.  I’d suggest at least talking with some of your peers and your team
you’ll be working with on a regular basis.  You don’t need to (or maybe can’t)
meet with everyone on the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-end-goal&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-end-goal&quot; aria-label=&quot;the end goal permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The End Goal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is new or too surprising.  You’re building relationships within
your team.  The big value here is in the asking and listening.  It shows a
respect to the existing team and paves the path to a level of trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll end up with more questions than answers, finding you don’t know more
than you thought - but at least you’ll know what you didn’t know.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Writing JavaScript Behavioral Unit Tests]]></title><description><![CDATA[When going through some old projects I realized that I hadn’t particularly kept
up with my game of life implementation in JavaScript.
I…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/writing-javascript-behavioral-unit-tests</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/writing-javascript-behavioral-unit-tests</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2014 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;When going through some old projects I realized that I hadn’t particularly kept
up with my &lt;a href=&quot;/gameoflife.js&quot;&gt;game of life&lt;/a&gt; implementation in JavaScript.
I never truly verified it worked.  Sure, it &lt;em&gt;looks&lt;/em&gt; like it worked
but how would I know for sure that it did?  Behavioral unit tests to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any live cell with fewer than two live neighbors dies, as if caused by under-population.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any live cell with two or three live neighbors lives on to the next generation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any live cell with more than three live neighbors dies, as if by overcrowding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any dead cell with exactly three live neighbors becomes a live cell, as if by reproduction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good representation of the behavior that should be exhibited by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://wikipedia.org/wiki/Conway%27s_Game_of_Life&quot;&gt;Conway’s Game of Life&lt;/a&gt; in plain, understandable English.
However, we are engineers!  We have to come up with some overly abstract and
strict way to represent these behaviors.  We need a specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;behavioral-specifications&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#behavioral-specifications&quot; aria-label=&quot;behavioral specifications permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Behavioral Specifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A behavioral specification is a document, not dissimilar from pseudo code, which
describes the expected behavior of a software unit.  While not entirely
necessary for writing tests these documents can flesh out what tests are needed
and reveal issues that may not be obvious otherwise.  As crazy as it may sound
it also creates a way for someone that is less technical to not only understand
what your tests do, but also verify that they match every behavior that is
expected of the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there is no right or wrong way to write a behavior specification, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dannorth.net/whats-in-a-story/&quot;&gt;structure proposed by Dan North&lt;/a&gt; is clear,
concise, and uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-text line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Story: Game of Life

As a cellular automaton simulation
I want to follow the rules of Conway&amp;#39;s Game of Life
So that we are able to simulate simple life

Scenario 1: Game of Life should kill lonely cells
Given that a cell is alive
 And that cell has no live neighbors
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should die

Scenario 2: Game of Life should kill cells with only one neighbor
Given that a cell is alive
 And that cell has exactly one live neighbor
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should die

Scenario 3: Game of Life should leave cells with two neighbors alone
Given that a cell is alive
 And that cell has two live neighbors
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should continue to live

Scenario 4: Game of Life should leave cells with three neighbors alone
Given that a cell is alive
 And that cell has three live neighbors
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should continue to live

Scenario 5: Game of Life should kill overpopulated cells
Given that a cell is alive
 And that cell has more than three live neighbors
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should die

Scenario 6: Game of Life should reproduce into cells with exactly three live neighbors
Given that a cell is dead
 And that cell has exactly three live neighbors
When a simulation step has executed
Then that cell should be given life&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-the-tests&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#writing-the-tests&quot; aria-label=&quot;writing the tests permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Writing The Tests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing unit tests in Jasmine is dead simple.  The hard part is   Just a minor translation.  We start by creating the directory &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;specs&lt;/code&gt;
and adding the file for our story in it, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;gameoflife.js&lt;/code&gt;.  We can start by
adding in a basic description of our story, as well as set up which will be used
by all of our tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a group of specs which will be our story, Jasmine provides &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;describe&lt;/code&gt;,
which accepts a description string and a callback.  Because the callback is
a normal JavaScript function we can define variables inside it which is exposed
to all of the specs.  The set up is achieved by using the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;beforeEach&lt;/code&gt; function
provided by Jasmine with the describe callback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-javascript line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;use strict&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;describe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;Game of Life&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// As a cellular automaton&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// I want to follow the rules of Conway&apos;s Game of Life&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// So that we are able to simulate simple life&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;beforeEach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        game &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;GameOfLife&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// No scenarios have been defined yet, but this is where they would go!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part the scenario test should be as basic as possible.  They have
already been defined in our Behavioral specification document, and can be
translated to our Jasmine tests.  The scenarios match up with specs using the
Jasmine provided function &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;it&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To verify behavior expectations are key to the tests, and the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;expect&lt;/code&gt; function
can be used.  Expectations in jasmine take the actual value as a parameter and
use method chaining to create matches.  There are many
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jasmine.github.io/2.0/introduction.html#section-Included_Matchers&quot;&gt;matchers included by default&lt;/a&gt; in Jasmine, but those
used most often are &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;toBe&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;toEqual&lt;/code&gt;.  While similar there is a definite
difference: &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;toBe&lt;/code&gt; tests if an actual matches a given expected result with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;===&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;toEqual&lt;/code&gt; tests if an actual matches a given expected result with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, scenario 1 and 2 could be represented with the following specs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-javascript line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Scenario 1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;should kill lonely cells&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Given that a cell is alive&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;spawnCell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// And that cell has no live neighbors&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;commit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// When a simulation step has executed&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;step&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Then that cell should die&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;expect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getInhabitants&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;length&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;toEqual&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Scenario 2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;should kill cells with only one neighbor&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Given that a cell is alive&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;spawnCell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// And that cell has exactly one live neighbor&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;spawnCell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;commit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// When a simulation step has executed&lt;/span&gt;
    game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;step&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Then that cell should die&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;expect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;game&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getInhabitants&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;length&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;toEqual&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;game&lt;/code&gt; variable has already been initiated in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;beforeEach&lt;/code&gt;
function in the spec definition, so we can use it in our scenario.  We use
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;expect&lt;/code&gt; - passing in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;game.getInhabitants().length&lt;/code&gt; - and use Jasmine’s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jasmine.github.io/2.0/introduction.html#section-Included_Matchers&quot;&gt;matching API&lt;/a&gt; to verify that it is equal to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;.
While not absolutely necessary, they also include the original document as
comments, to explain what the test is trying to do in case the tests are ever
questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this is a fraction of the scenarios, they all can be written in similar
fashion.  For the complete version of these specs written in Jasmine,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/imnotjames/gameoflife.js/blob/master/specs/gameoflife.js&quot;&gt;check them out on GitHub.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;npm-and-grunt-in-5-minutes&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#npm-and-grunt-in-5-minutes&quot; aria-label=&quot;npm and grunt in 5 minutes permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;NPM and Grunt in 5 minutes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While using NPM and grunt are not needed for using Jasmine it does simplify the
experience.  It takes a small amount of work getting it up and running but
could be an article in itself.  However, in just a couple minutes you can go
from arduously initiating tests manually to having grunt fly through them.  It
also bypasses the need of having a web browser open to run the tests by using
&lt;a href=&quot;http://phantomjs.org/&quot;&gt;phantomJS&lt;/a&gt; - a definite win.  If you haven’t already you should
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nodejs.org/download/&quot;&gt;install node&lt;/a&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If don’t have a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file you can generate one with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.org/doc/cli/npm-init.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;npm init&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  To add the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;grunt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;grunt-contrib-jasmine&lt;/code&gt;
dependencies you can run the command
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;npm install grunt grunt-contrib-jasmine --save-dev&lt;/code&gt; or manually edit the
package file. If you need to know anything else about the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;
file, you can always consult the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.org/doc/files/package.json.html&quot;&gt;npm documentation on the subject&lt;/a&gt;.  Once you’re
satisfied with your &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; running &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt; should fetch Jasmine,
grunt, and the grunt Jasmine task if you haven’t installed them already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, you still need a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gruntfile.js&lt;/code&gt; to run the tests.  The &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gruntfile&lt;/code&gt;
initializes the various tasks including our test runner.  The following is an
example &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gruntfile&lt;/code&gt; which assumes your Jasmine specs are in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;/specs/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-javascript line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;use strict&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

module&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function-variable function&quot;&gt;exports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token parameter&quot;&gt;grunt&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    grunt&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;initConfig&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        jasmine &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            src &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;src/**/*.js&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            options &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                specs &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;specs/**/*.js&apos;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    grunt&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;task&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;registerTask&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;test&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;jasmine&apos;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    grunt&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;loadNpmTasks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&apos;grunt-contrib-jasmine&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very basic example which only runs the Jasmine tests.  Grunt can do a
wide variety of tasks.  More information on setting up tasks in a
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gruntfile&lt;/code&gt; can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gruntjs.com/getting-started&quot;&gt;Grunt Documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;integrating-with-travis-ci&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#integrating-with-travis-ci&quot; aria-label=&quot;integrating with travis ci permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Integrating with Travis CI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous integration is an important part of keeping up to date with the
status of your software build.  Not only does it never forget to run your unit
tests, it runs them on many different environments at the same time.
Travis CI has an in &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.travis-ci.com/user/languages/javascript-with-nodejs/&quot;&gt;in-depth reference&lt;/a&gt;  on their
integration with node.js for a multitude of complex set ups. For anyone else
who just wants to get the Jasmine tests up and running with Travis CI, it’s one
of the more basic things to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default Travis calls &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;npm test&lt;/code&gt;, which refers to a predefined script. Add to
the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;scripts&lt;/code&gt; section and within that scripts section you must
define how you want your tests to be run.  Because grunt was configured with a
task called test in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Gruntfile&lt;/code&gt; above, adding &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;grunt test&lt;/code&gt; should be
sufficient.  For extra measure, and to aid in resolving any failures it is
a good rule of thumb to enable as much verbosity as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-json line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;scripts&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;test&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;grunt test --verbose&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, changes to the package definition alone won’t get a project ready to
be ran.  To tell Travis what language this is and how the environment must be
set up a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-yaml line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-yaml&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token key atrule&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; node_js
&lt;span class=&quot;token key atrule&quot;&gt;node_js&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;0.11&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;0.10&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;0.8&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token key atrule&quot;&gt;before_install&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;npm update -g npm&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;npm install -g grunt-cli&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of customization that can be done with the configuration file can be
a little overwhelming, but most everything that anyone could ever want to know
about Travis is in their  &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.travis-ci.com/&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.  However, with those two
changes in place all it takes is a commit, a push, and you can sign into Travis
and get it to start running continuous integration like all of those fancy
pants engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-point-of-it-all&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-point-of-it-all&quot; aria-label=&quot;the point of it all permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Point of it All&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day software that is written is worthless if it doesn’t behave
as it’s supposed to.  Even if broken software is better than no software, part
of being a professional is holding yourself to a higher standard than
“adequate”.  With everything set up not only can you verify after every change
that you’ve not broken the behavior of your systems, you also get feedback on
all commits automatically through Travis or other Continuous Integration
systems.  Nobody is always perfect, so testing is a valuable safety net for
when humanity hits and mistakes are made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of all, breaking the build should be lauded as a learning experience, not
shunned as a failure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[print_r is terrible]]></title><description><![CDATA[The short version: use , don’t use .  is to print human readable representations of a variable’s contents.
It is practically useless as a…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/print_r-is-terrible</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/print_r-is-terrible</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 16:22:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The short version: use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/code&gt;, don’t use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/code&gt; is to print human readable representations of a variable’s contents.
It is practically useless as a debugging tool.  It isn’t even useful for
humans to consume it because no human wants to read arrays or even think about
the concept of arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On first glance it kind of works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo bar&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
foo bar

php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those sure are some fantastic string representations of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you quickly find out that many things are printed as being the same value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;0&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;1&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When strings are involved, you also can get output that may look the same but
isn’t because of whitespace or other various non-visible characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo &apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;foo&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;chr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; foo 
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; foo
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; foo
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;..Or you get things caused by people who just want to watch the world burn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;Array\n\t\t(\n\t\t\t[0] =&gt; Wello\n\n\t\t)\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
                        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Wello

                &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;print_r&lt;/code&gt; does not display data in any structured manner and sacrifices
differentiating between types for the sake of readability.  While you are
debugging you don’t want readability.  You want to know what the variable
contains.  &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/code&gt; gets you that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo &apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;foo&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;chr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword type-declaration&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;foo &quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword type-declaration&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;foo&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword type-declaration&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;foo\000&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

php &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;0&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword type-declaration&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword type-declaration&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;0&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just use &lt;a href=&quot;http://php.net/var_dump&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  (Or be sane and set up &lt;a href=&quot;http://xdebug.org/&quot;&gt;xdebug&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Problems with Long Running PHP scripts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Writing a daemon in PHP can be a very attractive prospect.  You already have
your website written, so you have all of this great code…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/the-problems-with-long-running-php</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/the-problems-with-long-running-php</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2014 00:51:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Writing a daemon in PHP can be a very attractive prospect.  You already have
your website written, so you have all of this great code already.  You just need
it to run and keep track of some data or handle some data as it comes in by
polling a database.  All you do is.. make some infinite loop and..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token php language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter important&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$databse&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name static-context&quot;&gt;MyGreatLibrary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getInstance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$database&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;fetchNewData&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;empty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name static-context&quot;&gt;MyGreatProcessor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;process&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

			&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;ack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;catch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;fail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

			&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;error_log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string double-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&quot;Error with processor: &quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getTraceAsString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sleep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Wait for new data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yes.  Beautiful, we’re in business!  What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;php-isnt-meant-to-live-forever&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#php-isnt-meant-to-live-forever&quot; aria-label=&quot;php isnt meant to live forever permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;PHP isn’t meant to live forever&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest reason to let PHP die is that it is the intended use.  It’s a
system primarily designed to handle one request, die, and jump back up again,
resetting itself to a pristine condition - like some sort of ElePHPhoenix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you take that glorious death of the process away from it you’re fighting
what makes PHP so useful for the web - how it throws everything away after
each request.  When you try to work around this, and force PHP into roles
that it’s not fit for you’ve subjugated yourself to be tormented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also will be bypassing most knowledge that sane developers have
accumulated, and the standard PHP documentation will not be able to save you.
It’s lacking and even non-existant in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;memory-leaks-and-garbage-collection-problems&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#memory-leaks-and-garbage-collection-problems&quot; aria-label=&quot;memory leaks and garbage collection problems permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Memory Leaks and Garbage Collection Problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest problem with long running scripts has much to do with PHP’s
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.php.net/manual/en/features.gc.php&quot;&gt;garbage collection&lt;/a&gt;.  In recent versions it’s become a more advanced
system (version 5.3 and later) but it still can have quirks which may not be at
first the most obvious, especially to those who are used to managing memory on
their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something exacerbated because PHP itself never frees up memory back to
the operating system to dole out to other processes.  It will only allow it to
be reallocated by other PHP data.  This means that once it does allocate memory
to a PHP process, it continues to hold onto it until the process is ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases unset can be invoked and the garbage collection routines will
eventually get to them.  This is done by the internal implementation of
data structures in PHP keeping a &lt;a href=&quot;http://php.net/gc.refcounting-basics&quot;&gt;reference counter&lt;/a&gt;,
incremented at every occurrence of use of the reference, and decremented when
unset.  There are a few cases in which unset does not fully decrement the
reference counter.  One of which is if there is, surprise, a reference to the
data in some other area.  This could be if another object or variable points
to it, which at first thought may be straightforward may not always be easy to
detect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token php language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter important&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;parse_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;parsed&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;substr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;bar&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;original&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;stdClass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$variable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;file_get_contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;large_file.txt&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;parse_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$variable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$arr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;unset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$variable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// The references still exist to the zval that $variable pointed at&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other, more devious instance of data remaining in memory is cyclical
references, in that one object refers to another object which refers back to
the original object.  Even when you unset both of the references to the
objects, they still have a reference in that they refer to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token php language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter important&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$super&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;SuperGreat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;selfReference&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;unset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// $super&apos;s data continues to stay in memory unless&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// the garbage collector is enabled&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be resolved by enabling the more advanced garbage collection available
in PHP 5.3 and later.  This can be done either with the function &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;gc_enable()&lt;/code&gt;
or the php.ini setting &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;zend.gc_enable=1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, you’re still at the whim of the garbage collector, which will only
collect the unused references when the root buffer fills up.  Thus, calling
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;gc_collect_cycles()&lt;/code&gt; may be required in situations where memory is at a
premium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues with memory leaks do not always pertain to just your code,
either.  Many third party PHP libraries can be at fault as well.  If they don’t
follow the same strict rules regarding reference counting and hinting to the
garbage collector that data is available to be collected memory leaks can occur.
This does not get into extensions, which are often never meant to be running for
long periods of time and do have the ability to mismanage memory.  A good
example of this is PHP’s SPL library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token php language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter important&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Collection&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;extends&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;ArrayObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;protected&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;getIterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Well, this is a heavy object to make, let&apos;s memoize it&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;isset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;iterator&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;ArrayIterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$collection&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Collection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;foo&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;bar&apos;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;foreach&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$collection&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;unset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$collection&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;gc_collect_cycles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// Memory from collection is never freed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=53803&quot;&gt;bug opened&lt;/a&gt;, but no resolution aside from manually
destroying the cycles has come of it.  The reason that it happens is because,
as described in the bug, the garbage collector relies on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.php.net/internals/engine/objects#get_properties&quot;&gt;get_properties’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;HashTable&lt;/code&gt; to know which references
are held by a given object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a traditional request PHP cleans up all variables during shut down of the
engine in preparation for the next request.  As a long running script
intends to never shut down and allow that process to happen memory leaks
escalate from being a minor blip to taking down entire servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resource-descriptor-limit&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resource-descriptor-limit&quot; aria-label=&quot;resource descriptor limit permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Resource Descriptor limit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When opening a file, a connection to a database using some APIs, or working with
various extensions, you get back a resource instead of an object.  These
resources allow PHP to correctly communicate with the open stream you’ve
instantiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resource Descriptors, however are not a renewable resource in PHP as of the 5.5
release.  The counter is limited to 2^32 - 1.  What should happen is that
the open stream &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/functions/open.html&quot;&gt;should&lt;/a&gt; choose the lowest file descriptor not
currently open.  PHP, however, does not.  Once a resource is opened it can’t
be reused.  Closing it does not send it back to the available pool of
descriptors.  The &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=47396&quot;&gt;related bug&lt;/a&gt; has been open for nearly 4 years now,
so while it is possible that it’s being worked on, it is even more possible
that it will not be fixed for some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, seeing as there are then roughly 8.6 billion available
descriptors this is unlikely to be much of an issue in most real world
situations.  Just one of the many little problems that exist with running a
PHP script for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-minor-concerns&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#other-minor-concerns&quot; aria-label=&quot;other minor concerns permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Other minor concerns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With long running scripts one of the more lucrative features of PHP doesn’t
come into play, either - how it handles updates.  If PHP never shuts down
the code is never unloaded, and new code is never loaded back in.  This means
that a user would have to manually shut down the worker in some way, usually by
killing the process.  One way to work around this would be to keep track of
when the script was started and compare it against the modified time of the
file, then exiting when it is safe to do so.  Not a pretty way to handle
updates by far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many libraries rely on open connections to external services, and for a large
range of reasons that connection could be closed after a long enough time,
especially if the script is sitting in a “waiting” state for a while.
An example of such behavior could be the error message
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;MySQL server has gone away&lt;/code&gt;.  This requires boilerplate code to be in place,
verifying that the connection is fresh and available when processing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-i-do-about-it&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-can-i-do-about-it&quot; aria-label=&quot;what can i do about it permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What can I do about it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most cases the need for a long running script just isn’t there.  For some
people, PHP isn’t needed at all, and a language better suited for writing
daemons could be chosen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also are many techniques for handling the processing of data in the
background without using long running PHP scripts.  One such would be the use
of job queues and short lived PHP workers started by &lt;a href=&quot;http://supervisord.org/&quot;&gt;Supervisord&lt;/a&gt;,
such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://kr.github.io/beanstalkd/&quot;&gt;Beanstalkd&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gearman.org/&quot;&gt;Gearman&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.celeryproject.org/&quot;&gt;Celery&lt;/a&gt;.  Many
job queues allow configuration to limit the number of jobs workers will handle
before restarting, thus negating the problems that can crop up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible to write long lived PHP daemons.  That doesn’t mean it’s the best
use of anyone’s time, especially yours.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[RFC: Engine Exception; Erroneous Exceptional Errors]]></title><description><![CDATA[One of the flaws with PHP is the ways in which it handles engine errors.  However, might change in PHP 5.6. Most of the errors in PHP will…]]></description><link>https://notjam.es/rfc-engine-exceptions</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://notjam.es/rfc-engine-exceptions</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 05:21:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;One of the flaws with PHP is the ways in which it handles engine errors.  However, might change in PHP 5.6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the errors in PHP will emit a small amount of text, call the error handler, and allow the engine to continue.
However, there are a few errors which are emitted that do not call the error handler, and instead terminate the application.
Specifically, these are &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_CORE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_COMPILE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_PARSE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_USER_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_RECOVERABLE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;.  Of these,
only &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_RECOVERABLE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt; calls the error handler, but it still will abort the running script if not handled correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these errors are from seemingly innocuous conditions, such as calling methods on null values, creating incorrect SimpleXML, or
trying to load an invalid WSDL in SoapClient.  (If you’re using the SoapClient, though, you have other problems.)  Not only can one
of the error conditions end a running script without allowing any cleanup, it also breaks several assumptions programmers can have.
For example, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;finally&lt;/code&gt; construct and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;__deconstruct&lt;/code&gt; methods are always ran before PHP shuts down - unless of course a fatal error ends
it early.  There are some hacks to handle these behaviors slightly better using &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;register_shutdown_function&lt;/code&gt;, but they are just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;set_error_handler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$errno&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$errstr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$errfile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$errline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;E_RECOVERABLE_ERROR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$errno&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant boolean&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;__construct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name type-declaration&quot;&gt;DateTime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// A timestamp instead of a datetime object.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1383329451&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// int(1383329451) - we&apos;ve bypassed the hinting&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;var_dump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catching a recoverable fatal error may be even worse than handling an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;.  The code continues on once it is caught as if nothing happened.
Situations like type hinting errors caught will allow input of the wrong type to be allowed through.  Even if you set an empty error handler that
does not return anything, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_RECOVERABLE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt; will be silently ignored and PHP will blunder onward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;EngineException&lt;/code&gt; is the proposed solution to this problem, by Nikita Popov.  It is a move away from the errors of the past, towards catch-able
Exceptions where possible.  The RFC includes &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_ERROR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_RECOVERABLE_ERROR&lt;/code&gt; in the purge, though the attached patch as of this writing
mostly only delves into a small portion of the errors, but it does include wording for developers to avoid using fatal errors, and instead
use exceptions where possible.  The following code would now work, where as of PHP 5.5, it does not.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&lt;pre style=&quot;counter-reset: linenumber NaN&quot; class=&quot;language-php line-numbers&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$object&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$h&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;fopen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;lockfile&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string single-quoted-string&quot;&gt;&apos;r+&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;flock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;LOCK_EX&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;run&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;finally&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;flock&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;LOCK_UN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;fclose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;$h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;span aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; class=&quot;line-numbers-rows&quot; style=&quot;white-space: normal; width: auto; left: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a win for anyone who has written any long living PHP application, as well as for those who don’t want to rely on error handlers to
make an attempt to hastily exit from what should not be a catastrophic engine shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While backwards compatibility woes threaten to halt this RFC faster than any &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;E_FATAL_ERROR&lt;/code&gt;, it hopefully will push future development to not use fatal errors.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>